<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached the 30. of Ianuary last at Bletsoe, before the Lord Saint-Iohn and others concerning the doctrine of the sacrament of Christes body and blood, vvherein the truth is confirmed and the errors thereof confuted, by Edward Bulkley doctor of diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Bulkley, Edward, d. 1621?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1586</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17146</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4027</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109470</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845117</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845117</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9998</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17146)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9998)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 181:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached the 30. of Ianuary last at Bletsoe, before the Lord Saint-Iohn and others concerning the doctrine of the sacrament of Christes body and blood, vvherein the truth is confirmed and the errors thereof confuted, by Edward Bulkley doctor of diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Bulkley, Edward, d. 1621?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[100] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe for George Bishop,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1586.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Signatures:  A-F F¹.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9998:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9998:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched <hi>the</hi> 30. <hi>of Ianuary</hi> laſt at Bletſoe, before the Lord Saint-Iohn and others, <hi>Concerning the doctrine of the</hi> Sacrament of Chriſtes body and blood, VVherein the truth is confirmed, <hi>and the errors thereof confuied,</hi> by Edward Bulkley Doctor of Diuinitie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prou. 14.6.</bibl> The ſcorner ſeeketh wiſedome, and findeth it not: but knowledge is eaſie to him that will vnderſtand.</q>
            <p>LONDON. <hi>Printed by Iohn Wolfe</hi> for George Biſhop. 1586.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9998:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9998:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT honorable, and my very good <hi>Lord and Lady: Iohn Lord Saint</hi> Iohn, Baron of <hi>Bletſoe,</hi> and the Ladie Catherin his wife, grace, mercie, and peace from God our father, and Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat wiſe Philoſopher Plato in an Epiſtle to Dyoniſius King of Sicile,<note place="margin">Pag. 671.</note> hath a wiſe ſaying, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That is: It is great ſafetie not to write, but to learne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for thoſe that publiſh things in writing to the view of all, do make themſelues ſubiect to the ſharpe cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of many. Of whom, ſome will finde fault with the matter, and ſome with the manner of deliuering the
<pb facs="tcp:9998:3"/> ſame. And ſurely I ſuppoſe, there was neuer age more fertile then this, in bringing forth malicious momouſes, that are more ready to carpe &amp; repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the well doings of others, then any wayes to doe good themſelues. Yea there be many which by finding fault with other mens good and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable labors, ſeeke to procure to themſelues an opinion and fame of fine wittes, and ſinguler learning. Therefore for that I haue bene vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to be bitten with ſuch Theons teeth, and conſidering both the great abundance of bookes, whereof in my iudgement a great number might wel be ſpared, and the plenty of learned writers, which this learned age doth yelde, I not being ignorant of the meaſure of mine owne foote, but wel diſcerning my ſmal myte, from other mens great and many talentes, haue thought good to follow Platoes ſafe counſaile, in being rather a learner, then a writer. Inſomuch that hitherto I neuer publiſhed any thing in print, but one other ſermon preached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 14. or 15. yeares paſt at Paules
<pb facs="tcp:9998:3"/> croſſe, the which, that reuerend, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; learned man of bleſſed memory M. Thomas Leauer, not onely deſired me, but vpon my refuſall and deniall vehemently adiured and charged me in the name of God for to penne and to print. But that ſimple &amp; ſhort ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon was ſo handled in printing, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue 60. foule faultes being commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in it (ſuch is the great and intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable negligence of ſome printers, which deſerueth ſharpe puniſhment) that I haue bene euer ſince more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to continue Platoes ſafe courſe of not writing, but learning. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding whereas of late it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed your Lordſhippe to requeſt me to preach at the miniſtration of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly communion in your Church (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you haue there placed a man indewed with good giftes, who both is well able, and alſo diligently doth diſcharge that deuty) the which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I had performed in ſuch ſort as God by his ſpirite inabled me, it pleaſed your Ladyſhip to conceiue ſo good liking of it, that firſt you ſent, and after your ſelfe ſpake vnto me to giue you the
<pb facs="tcp:9998:4"/> ſame in writing, not onely for your own vſe &amp; inſtruction, but alſo for the reformation (if it might pleaſe god to giue good ſucceſſe thereunto) of the vnſound iudgement of ſome, whoſe well doing you greatly tender. The which your godly requeſt, tending to ſo godly an end, when I could with ſafety neither of conſcience, nor duty denie: I haue labored (although more willing to preach ſixe ſermons, then penne one) to ſatisfie your deſire. And for that there were others alſo at the ſame time, which moued me to the ſame effect as your Ladiſhip did, and were deſirous to haue copies thereof, whom without my ouer great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble I could not content: I haue by theſe cauſes bin vrged, and by ſome men perſwaded, to let it paſſe in print Hoping that as it liked your Honors, and the other godly hearers, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged that they were greatly edefied &amp; confirmed in the true do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine therein conteined, by hearing of it: ſo by the reading of it, ſome may be more eſtabliſhed in the truth, and others if they will lay away preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
<pb facs="tcp:9998:4"/> opinion, and wilful affection: <hi>&amp;</hi> according to the old law of the Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians will equally and indifferently heare both parties may be reformed by it.<note place="margin">Aeſchines cont. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> But it is very miſerable and lamentable to ſee, how ſtubburnly manie ſtand againſt the truth, and euen wilfullie ſhut their eies from beholding the cleare light thereof. Soe that they will neither heare the word of God preached, nor reade godly and learned bookes publiſhed for their inſtruction.<note place="margin">Zachar. 7.11.</note> Wherein they follow the ſteps of their forefathers, who refuſed to hearken, turned their backes, and ſtopped their eares that they might not heare, and hardened their hearts as an adamant, that they might not heare the lawe and the words which the Lord of hoſtes ſent in his ſpirite by the hands of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Prophets. Therefore great wrath hath comen from the Lord of hoſtes. But of theſe men I will not further at this preſent ſpeake, onely I beſeech God open their eyes, that they may ſee the miſerable eſtate wherein they ſtand, and that at the length they may
<pb facs="tcp:9998:5"/> turne from darkneſſe to light,<note place="margin">Acts. 26.</note> from the power of Satan vnto God, that they may receiue inheritance among thoſe that be ſanctified by faith in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. And to the end that this ſimple ſermon may be a better meane and inſtrument for the inſtructing of ſuch as be ſimply ignorant, and not wilfully peruerſe &amp; obſtinate, I haue inlarged the ſame more in penning, then I did in preaching. And haue added ſome diſcourſes, and ſundrie teſtimonies of auncient fathers, with places of popiſh and Ethniſh writers which in preaching, partly the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time would not permit me to vtter, &amp; partly of purpoſe I did omit, This ſermon I haue neither in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, nor penning ſought to beutifie with ornaments of words and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, which in theſe diuine &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly matters is not ſo needfull: but haue thought it ſufficient for me, to deliuer and ſet forth the plaine truth, in a plaine and ſimple phraſe, being more deſirous, that it may lighten the minds, and inſtruct the hearts of the hearers and readers of it, with ſound
<pb facs="tcp:9998:5"/> doctrine, and ſubſtance of matter, then tickle and delite their eares with a vaine ſound, or glittering ſhewe of wordes. The which ſimple ſermon ſuch as it is, for as much as your lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip requeſted me to preach it, and your Ladyſhip moued me to write it: I haue thought it moſt meete, to offer and preſent it vnto your Honors, as a true teſtimonie and token of my lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and dewtiful mind towards you for your great fauour ſhewed me, and ſundrie benefits beſtowed vpon me. And I humbly beſeech your Honors, that if you haue found and felt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of knowledge in Gods holie truth, and of true comfort, by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this &amp; ſuch other ſermons prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, as I am aſſured you haue, that then you would daily more and more increaſe &amp; go forward in the loue of the preaching of Gods word, and to imitate that noble example of that noble man of AEthiopia,<note place="margin">Act. 8.22.</note> who both read (&amp; that in his charet, trauailing by the way,) the Prophet Iſaias, and alſo heard Philip expound the ſame. Euen ſo that your Honors may daily
<pb facs="tcp:9998:6"/> more &amp; more grow in the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, feare, and obedience of God, Wherein true Nobilitie doth chiefely conſiſt, not onely daily and reuerent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reade the word of God your ſelues: but alſo diligently heare faithfull Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips, that is, godly and learned mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters truely expound and preach the ſame. Which is moſt needfull for you. For as that noble ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> profited by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but was conuerted vnto Chriſt by Philips preaching:<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14.</note> ſo it is chiefly the preaching of the Goſpel, which winneth vs vnto Chriſt, planteth faith, &amp; worketh repentance in vs, and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth &amp; ſtirreth vs vp to walke warely &amp; vprightly before the Lord our god. For as ſpice when it is bruſed, is of more force to ſeaſon, &amp; meat when it is chewed is more meete to noriſh vs: Euen ſo the word of god, when it is by expoſition as it were bruſed, chewed &amp; applyed vnto vs, is of more power to ſeaſon the corrupt humors that be in vs, &amp; effectually to feed vs, that we may liue in holines &amp; righteouſneſſe vnto God: for want &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt of the preaching of Chriſts goſpel, it is lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb facs="tcp:9998:6"/> to ſee how many fearfully fal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the grace of god. Therefore that your Honors may not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue, but alſo daily increaſe in the true worſhip and feare of God, loue earneſtly the preaching of gods word, let it be dearer vnto you than thouſands of gold and ſyluer, ſweeter than hony, &amp; the hony comb, &amp; hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger after it as your daily food:<note place="margin">Matth. 13 45.</note> eſteeme it for that pretious pearle which ought to be more dear vnto you, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al theſe earthly and tranſitorie things of the world, for all fleſh is graſſe,<note place="margin">Iſai. 40.</note> and al the glorie thereof, is as the flower of the fielde, which ſoone fadeth and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth away: but the word of our God abideth for euer, and ſhall make vs ſtand &amp; floriſh for euer in gods king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, if faithfully in our heartes we beleeue it, and obediently in our liues and conuerſation follow it.</p>
            <p>Thus aſſuring my ſelf that your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors will take in good part this my bolde aduenture in preſenting this ſmall mite and poore gift vnto you: I will forbeare from further troubling you: beſeeching God the father of mercie ſo to worke by his holy ſpirit in
<pb facs="tcp:9998:7"/> you, that you may be filled with the knowledge of his wil in al wiſedome,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 1.9.</note> and ſpirituall vnderſtanding, that yee may walke worthy of the Lord, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him in all things, being fruitfull in all good workes and increaſing in the knowledge of God. &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honors moſt</hi> humble in Chriſt Ieſus to commaund <hi>Edward Bulkley.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>At my houſe in VVoodhall <date>the 18. of Februarie. <hi>1586.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:9998:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Sermon preached by</hi> Edward Bulkley Doctor of Diuinitie at Bletſoe the 30. day of <hi>Ianuarie</hi> 1585. <hi>vpon the doctrine</hi> of the Sacrament of the body and blood of Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Matth. 26.26.</bibl> As they did eate, Ieſus tooke breade, and when he had bleſſed, he brake it, and gaue it to his diſciples, and ſaid: take ye, eate ye, This is my body. Alſo he tooke the cuppe, and when he had giuen thanks, he gaue to them, ſaying, drinke ye all of this, for this is my blood of the new Teſtament, which is ſhed for many for the forgiuenes of ſinnes. I ſay vnto you that I will not drinke henceforth of this fruite of the vine vntill that day, when I ſhall drinke it new with you in my Fathers kingdome. And when they had ſong a pſalme, they went out into the mount of Oliues.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the time did nowe drawe neare,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.2.</note> that our Sauiour Chriſt was to offer that ſweete ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſacrifice and oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of himſelfe vpon the Altar of the croſſe for our redemption &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:9998:8"/> reconciliation: it ſeemed good to his heauenly wiſedome to ordaine this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament to be a perpetuall memoriall, remembrance and pledge vnto vs of his death and paſſion vntill his comming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.25.26.</note> And becauſe the law did require the Paſchal lambe at that time to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, he comming not to breake, but to fulfill the lawe, that he might diſcharge all our breaking of the law,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.17.</note> did firſt with his diſciples according to the law eat the paſſouer, and ſo did put an end vnto the ſame, and then did inſtitute this his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to ſucceed in his Church for euer in the place thereof. That as he had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned baptiſme to ſuccéed in the roome of Circumciſion, ſo he would haue this Sacrament to ſucceed in the place of the Paſcall Lambe: and as they had béene Sacraments and ſeales of the olde Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament before his comming in the fleſh: ſo theſe might be after his comming ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and ſeales of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and couenant whereof we reade Hieremie. 31.31. and Hebrewes 8.8. Therefore the Euangeliſt in the firſt words of my text ſaith, <hi>As they did eat,</hi> Meaning that when they had eaten the
<pb facs="tcp:9998:8"/> Paſchall Lambe, then they did receiue and eate this his holie ſupper. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I may gather this, that it is not ſo vnlawfull (as ſome thinke) after the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and eating of ſome thing, to eate this bleſſed Sacrament. The which I ſpeake not for that I would haue men eate and drinke and fill their bellies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come to this holy ſupper, which with al reuerence and ſobrietie ought in Gods feare to be receiued: but to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſuperſtition of ſome, who think that if they (being in neuer ſuch infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and weaknes) do taſt neuer ſo little, they be thereby vnméete and vnworthy to receiue this holy myſterie, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon abſtaine from it. But if we did iudge rightly, we ſhould think, that not the receiuing into vs of a little of Gods creatures ſoberly with thankeſgiuing, &amp; that vpon infirmitie, doth make vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>méete communicants: but thoſe things that come out of vs, euen out of our hearts, as euill thoughts, murders,<note place="margin">Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. 15.15.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulteries, formeations, theftes, falſe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, ſlaunders are the things that defile vs, and make vs more loathſome vnto Gods maieſtie, than any leproſie
<pb facs="tcp:9998:9"/> vnto men. Theſe thinges make vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>méete geſtes for ſuch a celeſtiall banket, and vnworthy receiuers of this bleſſed Sacrament of Chriſts body and blood. Well ſaith Chriſoſtome: <hi>Non enim co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediſſe confuſionem nobis affert,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Geneſ. hom. 10.</note> 
               <hi>ſed mali quippiam egiſſe. i.</hi> Not to eate, but to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any wickedneſſe bringeth ſhame vnto vs. Therefore I exhort you to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from theſe and all other ſuch fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie ſinnes, and to come with cleare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences and good hearts to this holy ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And as touching meats, I wiſh men to refraine from them, when they come to communicate on this ſacrament, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be for ſome great infirmitie &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie &amp;c. Now it followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ieſus tooke bread &amp;c.</hi> Here the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt ſheweth two cauſes of this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, the efficient &amp; material cauſe. The efficient cauſe is Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God,<note place="margin">Iohn 1.29.</note> who is the lambe of God that taketh away the ſins of the worlde, who hath made peace betweene God and vs by the blood of his Croſſe,<note place="margin">Colloſ. 1.20.</note> &amp; hath reconciled vs in the bodie of his fleſh through death,<note place="margin">1. pet. 1.18.</note> who hath redéemed vs from our vaine conuerſation receiued
<pb facs="tcp:9998:9"/> by the traditions of our fathers, neither with gold nor ſiluer, but with his owne precious blood, who hath loued vs, hath waſhed away our ſinnes in his blood,<note place="margin">Apocal. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> &amp; made vs kings and prieſts vnto his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, euen this Ieſus our only Sauiour &amp; redeemer, hath ordained this holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for vs &amp; left it vnto vs, in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his death, &amp; for a gage of our ſaluation purchaſed thereby. Wherefore if Ieſus Chriſt and our ſaluation procured by him, be deare and pretious vnto vs: then alſo this ſacrament, which he hath deliuered vnto vs, and inſtituted for vs, to confirme our faith in him, ought to be deare and precious vnto vs. Therefore we ſhould be very carefull, that neither negligently we abſent our ſelues from it, nor vnreuerently come vnto it, nor that we make not ſmal account of it: for if we vſe to make great account euen of ſmall things, which our deare friends leaue vs at the houre of their death, in remembrance of them: How much more account ought we to make of this ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, how ſmall ſoeuer it ſéeme to the outward eye of fleſh &amp; blood, ſéeing that our deare redéemer Ieſus Chriſt, euen
<pb facs="tcp:9998:10"/> as it were at the houre of his death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quethed and committed it vnto vs, and hath left to be a neceſſary foode vnto our ſoules, that thereby we may dayly more and more grow vp in him. But hereof I ſhall haue occaſion hereafter further for to ſpeake, when I ſhal intreat of our dew preparation in comming to receiue this holy Sacrament. The ſecond cauſe touched in theſe words which is the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall: is bread, and wine, as after fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, which be the outward matter and elements of this ſacrament, and be holy ſignes of Chriſts bleſſed body of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred, and of his pretious bloodſhed for vs. And here that we may the better know the true nature and vſe of ſacraments, we are to vnderſtand that God in offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to vs our ſaluation purchaſed by Ieſus Chriſt, vſeth two things, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one is his words: wherein be contained his ſwéete and pretious promiſes of mercie grounded &amp; founded vpon Ieſus Chriſt: the other is externall ſignes which wée call ſacraments, &amp; be added to the word, for ſeales to ſeale &amp; to confirme vnto our conſciences the promiſes of the word, &amp; euen to ſet that before our eyes which
<pb facs="tcp:9998:10"/> the promiſes of gods word do ſound into our eares: for we are to marke this, that both the promiſes of the word, and alſo the ſacraments lead vs to one ſelfe ſame thing, that is to Ieſus Chriſt, in him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſéeke our ſaluation. for as the word doth this as appeareth by thoſe places before alledged out of Iohn, <hi>1.29.</hi> Col. <hi>1.20. 1.</hi> Pet. <hi>1.18.</hi> Apocal. <hi>1.5.</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite ſuch other: euen ſo do the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments lead vs as it were by the hand vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame, &amp; liuely ſet the ſame before our eyes. As for example: baptiſme doth teach vs to the eye, that euen as water waſheth away the vncleaneſſe of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: ſo Chriſts pretious blood which hee ſhed for vs cleanſeth vs from the filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and giltines of our ſins. And this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Chriſts ſupper teacheth and aſſureth vs, that euen as bread and wine féede, nouriſh, ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; comfort mans hart: ſo alſo Chriſt Ieſus who offred his body and ſhed his blood once for al &amp; euen for vs, féedeth, nouriſheth, ſtrengthneth, &amp; comforteth our féeble ſinful ſoules vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternal life. And theſe two things, his word, &amp; outward ſacraments, God hath from the beginning vſed, therby to offer
<pb facs="tcp:9998:11"/> our ſaluation to vs, &amp; to aſſure vs of his fauour. When God had created Adam &amp; Eue, and placed them in Paradiſe, he did not onely by word teach and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh them to ſerue and honour him their creator, but alſo he did ſet the trée of life in Paradiſe, which ſhould ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes, &amp; effectually teach them to imploy that life which they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of God to Gods glorie. When God had brought that fearefull floud vpon the world, for the horrible corruption &amp; wickedneſſe thereof, and did in mercie determine neuer in like manner to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it ſo againe,<note place="margin">Gen. 9.11.</note> he did not onely aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vs therof by his word and promiſe: but alſo the more to confirme it vnto vs, did ſet his bow in the clouds, that as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as we behold the ſame, we ſhould be aſſured of the performance of gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, as euen to this day appeareth. When it pleaſed God to accept Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham and his ſéede to mercy, he did not onely ſignifie the ſame to Abraham by making his couenant with him,<note place="margin">Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> that he would be his God, and the God of his ſéed, and that in his ſéed al nations of the earth ſhould be bleſſed: but alſo he gaue
<pb facs="tcp:9998:11"/> vnto him the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Circumciſion, to be a ſeale of this his couenant, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them that by that bleſſed ſéed Ieſus Chriſt, he would circumciſe the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkinne of their hearts, and cut away all their vncleanenes. And when God as it were renewed this couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites when he brought them out of Egypt, he did not onely giue his Law vnto them, wherein his couenant was conteyned: but alſo ordeyned the paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and many other ſacrifices to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the ſame vnto them, in being ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly figures and ſignes of Ieſus Chriſt to come, vpon whom the couenant was grounded. Euen ſo to confirme the new teſtament and couenant made with vs, wherof I made mention before:<note place="margin">Hierom. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.31. Heb. 8.8.</note> (which is the ſame in ſubſtance with the olde: but called new, becauſe it is renewed vnto vs in Ieſus Chriſt reueiled, &amp; ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with greater graces of Gods ſpirit) Chriſt hath ordeined ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber (as S. Auguſtine affirmeth) feweſt,<note place="margin">Auguſt. Epiſt. ad Ianuar. 118.</note> in obſeruation eaſieſt, in ſignification moſt excellent, that is, Baptiſme &amp; his holy Supper. And therefore our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt ſpeaking of the cuppe (as S.
<pb facs="tcp:9998:12"/> Luke and S. Paul report his words) ſaith.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.25.</note> This cup is the new teſtament in my blood, that is to ſay a ſacrament and ſeale of the new teſtament and couenant of God confirmed vnto vs in his blood. And this manner of teaching and dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering of things by theſe two kinds of things, words obiected to the eares, and outward ſignes to the eyes, it ſéemeth that we by the inſtinct of nature, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God, haue in like ſort receiued. for in conueighing of things from one to an other we obſerue the ſame order. As if a man make conueiance of lands or goods, he doth it by words and externall ſignes. If it be by words committed to writing for continuance, we vſe to thoſe writings wherein be contained graunts &amp; couenants to put ſeales, which ſerue for the further ratifying &amp; confirming of them. If a man take poſſeſſion of a peece of ground, he doth it not only by vttering certaine words, but for further confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation thereof, he diggeth vp, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a clod or péece of earth in his hand. If a man make a promiſe to do this or that, he doth it not onely by words and ſpéech, but for ratifying thereof giueth
<pb facs="tcp:9998:12"/> his hand. When a King or Quéene take vpon them the gouernement of a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, they do it not onely by certaine words, but alſo they haue a crowne ſet vpon their head and a ſepter put in their hand, which be outward ſignes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of that dignitie &amp; dominion which they receiue. And thus commonly wée deale in all other matters. Whereby we ſée and plainely perceiue, that our gratious God, hauing in mercy reſpect to our infirmitie, &amp; as it were humbling himſelf to our capacity, doth vſe the like meanes in offring to vs our ſaluation in Ieſus Chriſt, that we vſe in theſe earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly matters and affaires, that is to wit, his word wherin be contained his ſwéet promiſes of mercy,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.16.</note> that he will be our God, and we his people, that he will bée mercifull to our iniquities,<note place="margin">Heb. 8 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 12.</note> &amp; neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member our ſins any more: &amp; ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which being outward ſignes &amp; elements he doth annex vnto his word, to ſeale thoſe promiſes &amp; the more effectuallie to confirme them vnto our conſciences. Hereby as I ſaid we may learn the true nature and vſe of Sacraments, which is to ſeale &amp; confirme gods promiſes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:9998:13"/> vs, thereby to ſtrengthen our faith in them, and to be gages and pledges to vs of our ſaluation in Chriſt Ieſus. For this cauſe it is ſaid that <hi>Ieſus tooke bread.</hi> It now followeth: <hi>And when he had bleſſed &amp;c.</hi> The papiſts by bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnderſtand conſecrating, and by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration they meane a conuerting by the ſpeaking of certeine wordes, of one thing into another. But this is not true conſecration, but rather a magicall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation. neyther can they ſhewe any good Latine writer, that euer vſed this Latine word <hi>Conſecrare,</hi> in ſuch ſenſe: but it ſignifieth to dedicate a thing to a holy vſe. And ſo we do conſecrate the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, when by preaching gods word, rehearſing the inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieſus Chriſt, and calling vpon God by prayer, we do take the bread &amp; wine from a common vſe, to be a ſacrament of Chriſts bodie and blood giuen for vs, to be a ſeale of Gods promiſes, and a pledge of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in Chriſt Ieſus. This is our conſecration which is true conſecration: as for their ſecreat whiſpering of certain words to turne one thing into another, we will none of it, we are content they
<pb facs="tcp:9998:13"/> vſe it, which is more méete for wicked coniurers, then godly Chriſtians: But in this place by bleſſing is ment nothing els but thankſgiuing, as moſt plainelie appeareth in the next verſe: for wheras it is ſaid that Chriſt taking the bread did bleſſe, in the verſe following it is ſaid that he taking the cuppe gaue thankes. And whereas S. Matthew &amp; S. Marke ſay, that he taking the bread bleſſed:<note place="margin">Matth. 26.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Mark. 12.22. Luk. 22.19. 1. Cor. 11.24.</note> S. Luke and S. Paul ſay that he gaue thanks. Wherby it moſt plainly appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that bleſſing and thankſgiuing is al one: the which alſo is euident by that ſaying of S. Paul,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.16.</note> when thou bleſſeſt in the ſpirit, how ſhall he that occupieth the roome of the vnlearned, ſay Amen at thy giuing of thanks, ſéeing he knoweth not what thou ſaieſt? heere it is moſt plaine, that which S. Paul in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part calleth bleſſing, in the latter he calleth thanſgiuing. So that our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, when he bleſſed, gaue thanks to his heauenly father. And as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour did neuer taſt any of Gods crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but always (as the Goſpel ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) he gaue thanks to God his father, to teach vs that we ſhould walke in his
<pb facs="tcp:9998:14"/> ſteps, and whenſoeuer we receiue or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy any of Gods benefites, alwaies to giue God thanks for them, from whoſe hand &amp; gratious goodnes we do receiue them: ſo here at this time no doubt but our ſauiour Chriſt had a further reſpect, &amp; giueth tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks to his father, for his great &amp; infinite mercy to mankind, &amp; for that great &amp; wonderful work of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which he was then ready to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh. Whereby we haue in like manner to learne, that as we ought to giue God moſt hearty thankes for all good giftes which he giueth vs, &amp; al benefits that he beſtoweth vpon vs: ſo when we come to this holy Supper of Ieſus Chriſt, wée ought to conſider on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one ſide our owne myſery by ſinne, how that we be of our ſelues childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wrath, enimies of gods grace, vnprofitable ſeruants, yea &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall children, which are not worthie to be called or counted Gods children: &amp; on the other ſide gods great and infinite mercy, who ſpared not his owne deare ſonne but gaue him for vs to redéeme vs and reconcile vs to his mercy, and to be a ſpiritual foode to noriſh vs to eternall life. Of theſe ineſtimable mercies wée
<pb facs="tcp:9998:14"/> ought moſt ſpecially when we come to this holy table to bée mindfull and to giue God moſt harty thanks for them. Not onely in ſounding forth the praiſes of God with our tongues, but alſo in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoring carefully to yéeld holy obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God in our liues. And for this cauſe the godly fathers called this ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Euchariſtia</hi> which doth ſignifie thanks giuing, for that it being a pledge of our redemption &amp; ſaluation by Ieſus Chriſt, we ſhould when we receiue it, giue thanks vnto god for the ſame. The which I beſéech you as at all times, ſo ſpecially when yée come to this holy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly for to do,<note place="margin">Xenoph. lib. 1 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The old Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans condemned no ſin more greatly, nor puniſhed none more ſeuerely, then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnes. If therefore we be not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kful to God for his great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies powred vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs by Ieſus Chriſt, we ſhal not eſcape his fearefull and terrible plagues. It followeth. <hi>He brake it, and gaue it to his diſciples &amp;c.</hi> The brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the bread doth ſet forth vnto vs the breaking of Chriſts body, &amp; the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the wine the ſhedding of his blood vpon the croſſe for vs, for this ſacrament
<pb facs="tcp:9998:15"/> is as it were a glaſſe for vs to beholde Chriſt crucified in, &amp; hereunto we muſt apply all the holy actions vſed in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration thereof. So the giuing of the bread and wine repreſenteth vnto vs the giuing of Ieſus Chriſt for vs, once vpon the croſſe for our redemption, and dayly to be a ſpiritual food to nouriſh vs to eternall life. The receiuing alſo of the bread and wine into our bodies doth ſignifie &amp; ſhew vnto vs our inward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of Ieſus Chriſt into our hearts by faith,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.17.</note> by the which he dwelleth in vs as the Apoſtle ſaith, &amp; we be made fleſh of his fleſh,<note place="margin">5.30.</note> and bone of his bones. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer Chriſt did breake the bread, not to eat it all himſelfe as maſſe prieſts do,<note place="margin">Durand lib. 4. cap. 53.</note> nor to offer one part for the ſoules in heauen an other for them that be aliue, and the third for the ſoules in purgatory as it is alſo their vſe, but to diſtribute it to his diſciples, that they might take and eate it. And therefore my text ſaith, he brake it and gaue it to his diſciples ſaying take ye, eate ye, this is my body. Wherein we are to note that he ſaith not, looke vpon it, knéele and knock vnto it, and worſhip it, but he ſaith, Take ye, eat ye,
<pb facs="tcp:9998:15"/> promiſing then it ſhalbe his body vnto them: ſo that here is a commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and alſo a promiſe. The commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in theſe words: take ye, eate ye: the promiſe in theſe, This is my bodie, wherefore if we looke to be partakers of the promiſe, we muſt yeeld obedience to the commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which if we refuſe to doe, we cannot looke to be partakers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promiſe. As for example, God ſaith,<note place="margin">pſal. 50.15.</note> call vpon me in the day of thy trouble, and I will deliuer thée: if we obey the commaundement, and call vpon God in the time of our trouble, we may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of the performance of the promiſe that God will deliuer vs, then and in that ſort, as he knoweth to be beſt for vs, for our God is not more liberall in promiſing, then he is moſt faithfull in performing. But if we doe not in our trouble call vpon God, we cannot looke that he ſhould deliuer vs. Euen ſo here if we obey not Chriſtes commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and do not take and eate it, but looke, knéele &amp; adore it, we cannot looke that it ſhalbe Chriſts body vnto vs: for it is not further a ſacrament to vs, then we according to our ſauiours inſtitution
<pb facs="tcp:9998:16"/> do take and eate it. No ſaith B. Boner? I wil eaſily confute that:<note place="margin">In M. Philpots examinations.</note> is not a capon a capon vnleſſe I eat it? euen ſo ſaith he, it is a ſacrament and Chriſts bodie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we doe not receiue it. I anſwere that B. Boner had as it appeared by his fat face, greaſie belly, &amp; by his fooliſh rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning better ſkil in a fat capon, then in the doctrine of diuinity, and namely of this ſacrament: for a capon being a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural thing, is a capon, as bread is bread and wine is wine although they be not receiued: but a ſacrament being a thing not of nature, but by grace, is not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a ſacrament, then it is ioyned to Gods promiſe and inſtitution, &amp; applied to that vſe whereunto it was ordayned. The water which flowed in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes out of the rocke was a ſacrament of Ieſus Chriſt to the Iſraelits which drank of it,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.4.</note> as Saint Paul ſheweth: but whereas not onely the Iſraelits, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo their cattel did drink of the ſame wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, was it a ſacrament to the cattel? No. If one ſhould take the water wherein a child hath bene baptiſed, and apply it to ſome common prophane vſe, is it then a
<pb facs="tcp:9998:16"/> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? No. It is not a ſacrament fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then it is ioyned to Chriſts in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and one baptiſed in it. Euen ſo the bread and wine is no further a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then according to Chriſts inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and cammaundement it is taken &amp; eaten. Therefore to the Papiſts in their priuate maſſes not taking &amp; eating it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Chriſts commandement, but gaping &amp; knéeling to it, &amp; worſhipping it, which he hath neuer commanded,<note place="margin">Hierem. 7.31<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euer came into his heart as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaketh, it is not Chriſts body, but they commit moſt abhominable Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, in giuing that worſhip to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which is due to Chriſt the Creator who is bleſſed for euer. But further of this their Idolatrous adoration, I will not now intreat: but come to that which followeth. <hi>This is my body</hi> in expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of which words many reſpecting more the outward ſound of the wordes, then conſidering the ſimple ſenſe &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Ieſus Chriſt, haue bene fouly deceiued, and haue hereof gathered ſundrie great errors. And euen ſo the verie Euangeliſts do ſhew, that diuers more regarding the externall ſounde of
<pb facs="tcp:9998:17"/> Chriſts words, then marking his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, haue bene greatly deceiued. As when our Sauiour Chriſt warned his diſciples to beware of the leauen of the Phariſes and Saduces,<note place="margin">Matth. 16.6.</note> his Diſciples did thinke that he ſpake of outward breade, whereas his meaning was to admoniſh them to take heed of the ſower corrupt doctrine of the Phariſes and Saduces.<note place="margin">12.</note> So when our Sauior ſaid vnto the Iewes,<note place="margin">Iohn. 2.19.</note> deſtroy this temple, &amp; in three dayes I wil raiſe it vp againe, they thought that Chriſt had ſpoken of the materiall temple of Ieruſalem, and therfore they ſaid, fortie and ſixe yeares was this Temple a building, and wilt thou reare it vp in three dayes? But he ſpake of the temple of his bodie. In like maner when our Sauior Chriſt ſaid to Nicodemus,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.3.</note> except a man be born again he cannot ſee the kingdome of God. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus taking it groſly of the outward byrth, ſayd: how can a man be born that is olde? can he enter into his mothers wombe againe, &amp; be borne? But Chriſt ſpake of ſpiritual regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrought by the holy Ghoſt. Many ſuch other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples might be alledged, but I will
<pb facs="tcp:9998:17"/> content my ſelfe onely with that one of the Capernaits, the coſen germans, or rather deare brethren of our papiſts, for whereas our ſauiour Chriſt ſaid:<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.51.</note> I am y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liuing bread, which came downe from heauen: if any man eate of this bread he ſhall liue for euer: and the bread that I will giue is my fleſh, which I will giue for the life of the world. They groſly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding this of the carnal &amp; external eating of Chriſts fleſh, ſaid, how can this man giue vs his fleſh to eat? and againe this is an hard ſaying: who can heare it?<note place="margin">60.</note> But Chriſt ſpake ſpiritually of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and not of carnall eating of his fleſh, &amp; therefore he ſaith,<note place="margin">63.</note> it is the ſpirite that quickeneth, the fleſh profiteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: the words that I ſpeake vnto you are ſpirit and life. In like manner let vs in this matter take diligent héed that by too much grating vpon the letter, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the outward ſound of words, &amp; not conſidering Chriſts meaning we be not ſeduced and caried into errour, in groſſely and carnally taking that, which Chriſt our ſauiour ſpiritually &amp; ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tally did ſpeak.<note place="margin">Aduerſ. Praxca.</note> The counſel of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian herein is to be regarded and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed,
<pb facs="tcp:9998:18"/> who ſaith: <hi>Malo te ad ſenſum rei quam ad ſonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vocaboli exerceas. i.</hi> I would that thou exerciſe thy ſelfe rather to the ſenſe of the matter, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ſound of the word. Therefore that we may vnderſtand the true ſenſe &amp; meaning of theſe words, <hi>This is my body.</hi> We are to conſider, that it is no maruell, if our ſauiour Chriſt heare ſpeaking of a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, do ſpeak ſacramentally, and do vſe a phraſe of ſpeach vſual and common to all Sacraments, that is, to giue the outward ſigne the name of the thing ſignified. for whereas a ſacrament con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of two things, an earthly and an heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly as Irenaeus ſaith:<note place="margin">Lib. 4. cap. 14.</note> the outward element, and the thing wherof it is a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and that there is a ſimilitude &amp; agréeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t betwéene theſe two, as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: for as bread &amp; wine (as aboue I haue declared) do nouriſh, ſtrengthen, &amp; comfort mans heart &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: euen ſo doth Chriſts body and blood nouriſh ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthen &amp; comfort the ſoules of Gods children: by reaſon of this agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the name of the thing ſignified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the heauenly, is attributed to the ſigne being the earthly. And this is done
<pb facs="tcp:9998:18"/> for good and great reaſon, that we in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing this Sacrament ſhould not ſet &amp; fixe our minds vpon the earthly thing the bread and wine, but thereby be lifted vp to behold the heauenly thing, that is the body &amp; blood of Ieſus Chriſt giuen for vs. This doctrine the auncient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do moſt plainely ſet downe, how ſtraunge ſoeuer it ſéeme to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fauorers of the rotten &amp; ruinous Religion of Rome. Auguſtine writeth thus:<note place="margin">Auguſt. Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>facium</note> 
               <hi>Si enim ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta quandam ſimilitudinem &amp;c. i.</hi> 
               <q>If ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments had not a certaine ſimilitude and likeneſſe of thoſe things whereof they be ſacraments, they were no ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at all. And by reaſon of this ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude they do often take the names of thoſe things. As therefore after a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſort, the ſacrament of Chriſtes bodie is Chriſtes bodie and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Chriſtes blood is Chriſts blood, ſo the ſacrament of faith is faith. And againe,<note place="margin">Auguſt. Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. queſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</note> 
                  <hi>Solet autem res quae ſignificat eius rei nomine quam ſignificat nuncupari &amp;c.</hi> The thing that ſignifieth is wont to be called by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing which it ſignifieth, as it is written, the ſeuen eares of corne are ſeuen yeares: for hée
<pb facs="tcp:9998:19"/> did not ſay,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 41.26.</note> they ſignifie ſeuen yeares? And the ſeuen kine be ſeuen yeares, and many ſuch like. Hence commeth it that was ſaid. <hi>The Rock was Chriſt,</hi> for hée ſaid not <hi>The Rock</hi> doth ſignifie <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but as though it were that, which in truth by ſubſtance it was not, but by ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In like manner doth Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doretus in his firſt Dialogue<note place="margin">Theodoretus dialog. 1.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. Therefore our ſauiour chaunged the names,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> &amp; to his bodie hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of the ſigne, &amp; to the ſigne the name of his body. So he that called himſelf a vine, hath alſo called the ſigne his body. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. This thou haſt ſpoken truely, but I would learne the cauſe of this change of the names<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The ſcope &amp; end is euident to them that be inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in diuine matters. for our Lord would that they which be partakers of the diuine miſteries, ſhould not ſet their minds vpon the nature of the things that are ſéene, but by the chaunge of the names, to beléeue the chaunge that is wrought by grace: for he that called his naturall body wheat and breade, and againe called himſelfe a vine: the ſame hath honored the viſible ſignes
<pb facs="tcp:9998:19"/> with the name and title of his bodie and blood, not chaunging nature,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> but adding grace vnto nature: hitherto Theodori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</q> In which words he flatly affirmeth that the name of the thing ſignified is giuen to the outward viſible ſigne, and ſheweth the cauſe and reaſon why it is ſo done. And that it is a vſual and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon phraſe (as I ſaid before) in al ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments it is moſt plaine by many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the ſcripture.<note place="margin">Cap. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hoc eſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctum pag. 13 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> In Geneſis God ſaith of Circumciſion: This is my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant. And againe: My Couenant ſhalbe in your fleſh. Here Circumciſion is called the Couenant, and yet it was not the Couenant: for this was the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, that God would be God to him, and to his ſeede after him &amp;c, of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant Circumciſion was a ſigne and ſeale, as in the ſame place is ſaid: yée ſhall circumciſe the foreſkinne of your fleſh,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 17.11.</note> and it ſhalbe a ſigne of the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant betwéene me and you. This Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion which was a ſacrament and ſigne of Gods Couenant, is called the Couenant it ſelfe, to the end they vſing &amp; remembring it, might be put in minde of Gods Couenant which it ſignified,
<pb facs="tcp:9998:20"/> ſealed,<note place="margin">Exod. 12.11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtenim phaſe (i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt tranſitus) domini.</note> and confirmed vnto them. So the Paſchal lambe is called the paſſeouer in theſe words: Yée ſhall eate it in haſt, for it is the Lords paſſeouer. And againe: Chooſe out and take ye for euery of your houſeholds a lambe, and kill the paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. So our Sauiour Chriſt alſo calleth it in this Chapter:<note place="margin">Verſ. 18.</note> I wil kéepe the paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer at thine houſe with my Diſciples. Here yée ſée that the lambe is called the paſſeouer: and yet the lambe properly was not the paſſeouer, for the paſſeouer, was the paſſing of the Angel ouer the houſes of the Iſraelits, where the blood of the lambe was ſprinckled, when he deſtroyed the firſt borne of the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Now the Lambe was a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, holy ſigne, and pledge of this paſſeouer and deliuerance, and ſo conſequentlie of that true deliuerance from eternall deſtruction and damnation by Ieſus Chriſt. The ſacrifices in the olde Lawe were called ſinnes, becauſe they were offred for ſinne: in which ſenſe God by the Prophet ſaith of the prieſts, they eat vp the ſinnes of my people,<note place="margin">Hoſe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8.</note> meaning the ſacrifices which they offered for the ſins of the people. So likewiſe Chriſt is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:9998:20"/> ſinne: He that knew no ſinne,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.21.</note> was made ſinne for vs, that we ſhould bée made the righteouſneſſe of God in him. The Rocke is called Chriſt. The Rock was Chriſt ſaith S. Paul,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.4.</note> yet the Rock was not properly Chriſt but a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt. But to come nearer to this matter.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Saint Paul ſaith the bread which we breake, is it not the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Chriſt? in which words he meaneth and affirmeth bread to bée the communion of the body of Chriſt. And yet properly bread is not the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the body of Chriſt, but a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament and pledge of that ſpirituall communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which we haue with Chriſt, for as the bread receiued into our bodies is ioyned vnto vs, and made ours: ſo Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt receiued by faith into our ſoules is made ours:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.17. 1. Iohn. 1.3. Epheſ. 5.30.</note> &amp; we haue fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with him, yea and be made fleſh of his fleſh and bone of his bones. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer whereas Chriſt ſaith (as S. Paul recordeth) This cuppe is the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament in my blood &amp;c.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.25.</note> I would aſke of theſe men that grate ſo earneſtly vpon the letter, and vrge ſo eagerly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the word: whether the cup that is made
<pb facs="tcp:9998:21"/> either of ſiluer, gold or wood, (for by the way as Bonifacius the martyr ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſaid.<note place="margin">B. Rhenanus in Annotat. in Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull. de Corona militis.</note> In old times we had wooden Chalices and golden prieſts, but in theſe dayes we haue golden Chalices and wooden prieſts) be the new Teſtament? No, no, ſay they: by the cuppe is ment by a figure, the thing in the cup. Thus they that haue cried out againſt figures and figuratiue ſpeeches in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and haue ſcornefully called ſuch as haue vſed them figurators,<note place="margin">M. Anto. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius fol 2. &amp;c. tibi ſaepe.</note> are now forced to flée to a figure, to forſake <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>i.</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe words, and by the cuppe to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the thing contained in the cuppe. But to graunt them this, what is in the cup? wine ſay we, blood ſay they. Now to grant them this their owne aſſertion for diſputation ſake: I will aſke them whether blood be the new Teſtament? I ſuppoſe they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not with any forehead or face ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> blood is the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for what is the new Teſtament, but the new leage &amp; couenant which God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth with vs in Chriſt Ieſus, as it is ſet forth in Ieremie and the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes in theſe words:<note place="margin">Hierem. 31.31. Hebr. 8.10.</note> This is the Teſtament that I will make with the houſe of Iſrael, after thoſe dayes ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:9998:21"/> the Lord, I wil put my Lawes in their minde, and in their heart I will write them, and I wilbe their God and they ſhalbe my people. I wil be merciful vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their vnrighteouſneſſe, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member their ſinnes and their iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties no more. This promiſe of mercy is the new Teſtament: And therfore nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wine nor blood is properly the new Teſtament, but a Sacrament, a holy ſigne and ſeale of the new Teſtament, confirmed vnto vs in the blood (not of Oxen or Goats) but of Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God. Whereupon I thus rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with the Papiſts: as the Cuppe or that in the cuppe, is the new teſtament, ſo is the bread the body of Chriſt: but neither the cuppe nor the thing in the cuppe is properly the new Teſtament, but a holy ſigne and Sacrament of the new teſtament: So the bread is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the body of Chriſt, but a holy ſigne, and pledge of his body offred vpon the croſſe for vs. And this phraſe of ſpeach in attributing to the Sacrament the name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing whereof it is a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which ſéemeth ſo rough in theſe fine mens mouthes: both the ſpirite of God in the holy ſcriptures, &amp; we in our
<pb facs="tcp:9998:22"/> common talke vſe to giue too bare &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſignes, which do not exhibite as ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts do the thing ſignified, but bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſignifie the ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as in the example before alledged by S. Auguſtine,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 41.26.</note> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thinne eares of corne, and the ſeuen leane kine are ſaid to be ſeuen yeares, when as they did but onely barely ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the ſeuen yeares of famine which were to come.<note place="margin">Geneſ. 40.11.</note> So alſo Ioſeph ſaith of the thrée branches of the vine, and of the thrée white baſkets, the thrée braunches be thrée dayes, and the thrée white baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets be thrée dayes:<note place="margin">16.</note> when they did but onely ſignifie the thrée dayes, wherein the butler ſhould be reſtored, and the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker hanged. So S. Paul calleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiues vaile or couering of her head,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.10.</note> her power being but a bare ſigne of her huſbandes power ouer her, and many ſuch other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples might be alledged out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures but theſe ſhal ſuffice. In our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſpeach we vſe to call bare pictures, by the names of thoſe perſons whereof they be pictures.<note place="margin">Alluding to the pictures which hang in my lord S. Iohns great Chamber.</note> So we ſay this is king Henry the ſeuenth, this is king Henrie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eight, this is Francis the french king, this is the Lord Cromwal, and yet thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:9998:22"/> pictures be not thoſe perſonages, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and barely repreſent them. Now if we vſe to ſpeak thus of pictures, which be but bare ſignes of men, and do but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repreſent the formes &amp; ſhapes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. How much more may we ſo ſpeake of this Sacrament and call it the body and blood of Chriſt, being not a bare ſigne &amp; repreſentation thereof, but an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods grace whereby the bodie and blood of Chriſt is truly offered to all, and effectually receiued of the faithfull children of God, to nouriſh and comfort their ſoules. Yea moreouer the very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Poets haue vſed this phraſe of ſpéech, as Virgil ſaith <hi>faliere dextras</hi> for to breake promiſe, where by <hi>Dextras</hi> the right hands he meaneth promiſes made by giuing the right hand.<note place="margin">Iliad. 3.</note> So Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſaith: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>i.</hi> The Herolds brought from the citie the faithfull othes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gods, two lambs, pleaſant wine, the fruite of the earth. And againe: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Ibidem poſt.</note> 
               <hi>i.</hi> but the gorgeous Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolds brought forth the faithful othes of the gods. In which places by the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb facs="tcp:9998:23"/> othes, are ment the lambs and wine which they ſlew and powred out in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of thoſe promiſes, made tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the combate betwéene Menelaus and Paris, and ſo Euſtathius vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it: expounding <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the faithful othes, that is the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices. Where we ſée that the external ſacrifices, the lambes ſlaine and wine powred out, to confirme thoſe othes, that they which did not performe them, might be ſlaine, and their blood &amp; braines powred out as thoſe lambes and wine were, are called the othes themſelues. Theſe places to this end only I alledge to ſhew vs that it ſhould not ſéeme ſo ſtraunge a thing, to attribute to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſigne and Sacrament the name of that thing wherof it is a ſacrament, and for the confirming whereof vnto vs it is ordained and vſed. But that this expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mine or rather of God himſelfe, as hath béene proued by many places and reaſons out of the ſcripture, may plainly appeare to agrée with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of the auncient and godly fathers of the Church I will ſet downe ſome places out of their bookes, to be as witneſſes to
<pb facs="tcp:9998:23"/> giue teſtimony to the truth of this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. Tertullian ſaith,<note place="margin">Lib. 4. aduerſ. Marcionem.</note> 
               <q>Chriſt profeſſing that he did greatly couet to eat the paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer as his owne (for it were vnméete that God ſhould couet that which were an others) taking the bread and diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it to his diſciples, made it his bodie ſaying, this is my bodie, that is to ſay, a figure of my bodie: but it ſhould be no figure, vnleſſe Chriſts bodie were a true bodie, for a vaine or void thing, ſuch as is a ghoſt, cannot haue a figure.<note place="margin">Phantaſma.</note>
               </q> Héere Tertullian expoundeth theſe words. <hi>This is my body,</hi> by this that is figure of my body. And by this reaſon prooueth our Sauiour Chriſts bodie to be not <hi>ſpectrum</hi> or <hi>phantaſma</hi> a ghoſt or phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall body, as Marcion that monſter blaſphemed, but a true body like vnto ours, becauſe the Sacrament is a figure of it, which it could not be except it were a true body. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Papiſts doctrin in this point ſauoreth ſtrongly of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions blaſphemie, for to ſay that Chriſts body is in heauen and earth, yea and in infinite places of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth at one inſtant, and that the natural real body of Chriſt is vnder the formes of bread and wine,
<pb facs="tcp:9998:24"/> without any forme, quality, or quantity of a body without breadth, length, or thicknes, what is this but to make it no true body as Martion did. And euen ſo S. Auguſtine intreating of Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſaith:<note place="margin">Epiſt. 57. ad Dardanum.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpatia locorum tolle corpori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, nuſque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> erunt, &amp; quia nuſquam erunt, non erunt, Tolle ipſa corpora qualitatibus corporum, non erit vbi ſint, &amp; ideo neceſſe eſt vt non ſint. i.</hi> for take from bodies the ſpaces of place, &amp; they ſhalbe no where: and becauſe they be no no where, they be not at al. Take the bodies from the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of bodies there can be no place where they may be and therfore it muſt of neceſſitie be that they be not.</q> But the Papiſts attribute neither place nor qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to Chriſts bodie in the ſacrament, &amp; therefore by S. Auguſtines iudgement they make it no body, and ſo as I ſaid agrée in one with that monſter Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. But to returne to my purpoſe and to ſhew that the fathers haue expounded thoſe words of our ſauiour Chriſt in that ſenſe which I haue before declared. Auguſtine ſaith: I may expound that commaundement to be put in the ſigne,<note place="margin">Lib. cont Adu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantum Mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. diſt. cap. 12.</note> for our Lord did not doubt to ſay, <q>This
<pb facs="tcp:9998:24"/> is my body: when he gaue a ſigne of his bodie.<note place="margin">In Pſal. 3. in 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or. 11.</note> Again he admitted him (Iudas) to the feaſt wherein he commended and deliuered to his diſciples a figure of his bodie and blood. Ambroſe ſaith:<note place="margin">De iis qui initi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur. cap. 9.</note> In ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drinking we do ſignifie the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and blood of Chriſt which were offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for vs. Againe,<note place="margin">De Conſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra. diſt. 2. cap. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uera.</note> before Conſecration it is named an other kind, after Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration the bodie of Chriſt is ſignified.</q> The gréeke Fathers in like maner call the ſacrament a ſigne, figure, or token of Chriſts body. <q>Gegory Nazianze<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<note place="margin">Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> how dare he (which firſt hath not offred him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a liuely ſacrifice) offer to God that outward ſacrifice, which is a ſigne or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of thoſe great myſteries: and the like he hath in his oration vpon his ſiſter Gorgonia. Baſile ſaith:<note place="margin">Pag. 56. In Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgia. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> he hath left vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs memorials or remembrances of his paſſion by which commeth ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which according to his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement we propound vnto you. So Theodoritus <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Tell me therfore,<note place="margin">Dialog. 2.</note> thoſe myſticall ſignes which of the prieſts bee offered to God, of what things be they ſignes? <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Lords bodie and blood.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of his true bodie or not of his true
<pb facs="tcp:9998:25"/> bodie or not of his true bodie? <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of his true bodie <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. verie wel, for an image muſt haue a patterne whereof it is an Image,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> euen as Painters alſo do imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate nature, and paint the images of thoſe things that be ſéene. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that is true <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> if then the diuine myſteries be ſignes or figures of a true bodie, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of our Lord is yet a bodie, not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into the nature of the godhead, but repleniſhed with diuine glory.<note place="margin">Homil. 27. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </q> So ſaith Macarius: In the Church is offered bread and wine, examples of his fleſh and blood. Theſe places (that I alledge no moe) ſufficiently ſhew that it was not ſtraunge to the godlie fathers, to call this ſacrament a ſigne, token, figure, and example of Chriſts bodie, and that they vnderſtood theſe words, <hi>This is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,</hi> in that ſenſe, the bread to be called Chriſts bodie, becauſe it is an holie ſigne, example and pledge of Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die offred vpon the croſſe for vs.</p>
            <p>Now although I may ſeeme to haue ſufficientlie ſpoken of the true ſenſe and meaning of theſe words <hi>This is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,</hi> &amp; withall to haue opened the true doctrine of this ſacrament: yet becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:9998:25"/> many men be not as yet ſatiſfied in this point, but the popiſh doctrine of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, and carnall preſence of Chriſts bodie vnder the formes of bread and wine, ſticketh ſtill in their ſtomaks, I haue thought it very néedfull further to proſecute this matter, and more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, and largely to confute the ſaid errors, and to lay open the nakedneſſe and weakneſſe of them. The falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Papiſts, concerning their Tranſubſtantiation, which they cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly gather of thoſe words of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt conſiſteth in two ſpeciall points, the one, in that they ſay, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the words of Conſecration there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth no ſubſtance of bread and wine but onely the outward accidences there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as whitenes, roundnes, &amp;c. The other that the very naturall bodie of Chriſt, which was borne of the bleſſed virgin is there vnder the ſaid formes of bread and wine. As touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt, that there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maneth no ſubſtance of bread &amp; wine. I ſay that this is contrary to the holy ſcriptures, contrary to the writings of the auncient godly fathers, contrarie to the iudgement of all our ſenſes, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb facs="tcp:9998:26"/> to the nature of a Sacrament, &amp; laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch a doctrin as bringeth with it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny abſurdities.<note place="margin">Matth. 26.29.</note> That it is contrary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures I proue it thus. Chriſt ſaith I wil drinke no more of the fruit of this vine, vntill that day, that I ſhall drinke it with you new in the kingdome of my father. Our Sauiour Chriſt heere ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his ſupper and after his ſupper, calleth it the fruit of the vine, which is wine and not blood. S. Paul ſaieth the bread which we break is it not the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the bodie of Chriſt?<note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.16.</note> S. Paul here not onely ſaith that bread is the Communion of Chriſts body, but alſo ſaith. <hi>Which we breake.</hi> Now what do we breake? onely accidences without a ſubſtance? that is an abſurd follie: or doe we breake Chriſts body? as Pope Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas with his counſell compelled that learned man Berengarius to affirme,<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Conſec. diſt. 2. cap. Ego Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rengarius.</note> but that is wicked blaſphemie. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is manifeſt, that that which is broken is bread, and that bread bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, is the communion of the bodie of Chriſt, that is (as I before declared) a Sacrament and pledge vnto vs of our ſpirituall, and yet true and effectuall
<pb facs="tcp:9998:26"/> communion with Chriſt Ieſus. Againe S. Paul ſaith immediatly after:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.17.</note> we that are many, are one bread, and one bodie, becauſe we are all partakers of one Bread. Againe, as often as ye ſhall eate this <hi>Bread,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.26.</note> and drinke of this cuppe yée ſhew the Lords death till he come. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, whoſoeuer ſhall eate this <hi>Bread</hi> and drinke the cuppe of the Lord vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthely, ſhalbe guiltie of the body and blood of the Lord: And again, let a man therefore examine himſelf and ſo let him eate of this <hi>bread</hi> and drink of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his cup. Here Saint Paul fiue times call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th it <hi>bread</hi> euen when it is receiued and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, therfore I conclude that it is bread. But here the Papiſts come in with a craftie cauillation and think they haue found a fine deuiſe to ſhift off theſe plain words of the Apoſtle, they ſay that ſaint Paul calleth it bread, becauſe it was bread, as Aarons rodde being turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſerpent,<note place="margin">Exod. 7.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and being a ſerpent is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a rodde: Aharons rodde deuoured their roddes. I aunſwere firſt that they compare things vtterly vnlike: for in the Sacrament there muſt continue a ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude and agréement betwéene the ſigne
<pb facs="tcp:9998:27"/> and the thing ſignified, as before out of S. Auguſtine I declared, and therefore the ſubſtance of the ſigne muſt néeds re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, without which there can bée no ſuch ſimilitude. But in this matter there is no ſuch agréement betwéene the rodde and ſerpent, but rather bee cleane contrary, and therefore the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of theſe two are not alike. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly I ſay, that becauſe the conuerſion of the rodde into a ſerpent was but tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, &amp; for a ſhort time to continue, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes had good cauſe to call it a rodde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thereunto it was ſtraight wayes to be reſtored, and in the nature of a rod to continue. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly let the Papiſts ſhew that their bread is ſo turned into the bodie of Chriſt, as that rodde was into a ſerpent, and then they ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, other wayes they proue nothing. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly I may turne this Argument vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their owne heads, that as Moſes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſerpent a rodde, when it was not a rodde indéede but a ſerpent. So Chriſt called the bread his body, when it was not indéede naturally his bodie, but in ſubſtance bread, and by his ordinance a ſacrament of his bodie. And as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts
<pb facs="tcp:9998:27"/> will haue Saint Paul to call that bread, which they ſay is not bread: ſo why may not our ſauiour Chriſt call that his bodie, which not properly but ſacramentally is his body. Thus I truſt this their cauillation is ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed &amp; that you plainly perceiue that S. Paul calleth it bread, becauſe it is bread. The which now. <q>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Dialog. </seg>1</label> I will proue by the teſtimonies of the ancient fathers The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoritus beſide that plaine place before alledged, where he ſaith that Chriſt hath honored the viſible ſignes with the title or name of his bodie &amp; blood, not chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the nature of them, but <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Dialog. </seg>2</label> adding grace to nature: hath a more plaine and pregnant place, whoſe words be theſe: Thou art catched in thine owne ſnares, for the myſticall ſignes after ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or conſecration, leaue not their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per nature, but they remaine in their former <hi>Subſtance, and figure, &amp; kind,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c.</note> and be viſible and tangible as they were before, here not only Theodoritus plain words do affirme the nature and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of bread and wine to remaine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alſo the whole drift of the diſputation, betwéene the true
<pb facs="tcp:9998:28"/> Chriſtian, &amp; the Eutican heretike, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the ſame end.</q> But if the doctrine of tranſubſtantiation had beene then in the Church receiued, it had moſt fitly ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued for the heretiks purpoſe, that as the bread after conſecration, is turned into Chriſts body: ſo Chriſts bodie after the aſcention is turned into the deitie, and ſo the heretike reaſoneth but the true Chriſtian anſwereth that he is catched in his own ſnare, for as bread and wine after conſecration are not turned into Chriſts bodie and blood, but remaine in ſubſtance as they were before: ſo Chriſts bodie after his aſcention is not turned into the deitie, but repleniſhed with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and immortality.</p>
            <p>Gelaſius a Biſhop of Rome writing againſt the ſame heretike Eutiches that Theodoritus did, and vſing the ſame reaſon, ſetteth downe the ſame doctrine in theſe words:<note place="margin">Gelaſius contra Eurichen.</note> 
               <hi>Certe Sacramenta &amp;c. i.</hi> 
               <q>Surely the ſacraments of the bodie and blood of Chriſt, which we receiue are a diuine thing: and therefore by them wée be made partakers of the diuine nature, and yet it ceaſeth not to be the ſubſtance or nature of bread and wine, and indeed
<pb facs="tcp:9998:28"/> an image and ſimilitude of the bodie and blood of Chriſt is celebrated in the Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the myſteries &amp;c. Chriſoſtome alſo writeth thus:<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. ad C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarium Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chum.</note> 
                  <hi>Sicut enim antequam ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctificetur panis &amp;c.</hi> For as before the bread is ſanctified, we call it bread, but when the diuine grace hath ſanctified it, by the meanes of the prieſt, it is in déed deliuered from the name of bread, and is counted worthy of the name of the lords bodie, although the nature of bread doe ſtill continue in it, and is called not two bodies but one bodie, of the ſon &amp;c.</q> Both the words of Gelaſius, &amp; Chriſoſtome, and alſo the drift of their diſcourſes ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſame end that Theodoritus doth, moſt plainly ſhew, that after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration the ſubſtance of bread remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, euen as after Chriſts aſſention the ſubſtance of his true body continueth, or elſe theſe reaſons taken from the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament do not only not make for them but directly againſt them, yea and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make for thoſe heretikes whom they by theſe arguments ſéeke to confute. Origen alſo ſaith: <hi>Panis ille &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Orig. in Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. cap. 15.</note> 
               <q>That bread which is ſanctified by the word of God and prayer, according to the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial
<pb facs="tcp:9998:29"/> ſubſtance which it hath goeth into the belly, &amp; is caſt out into the draught, but by the prayer which is ioyned to it, according to the proportion of faith is made profitable.</q> By which it appeareth that it is the ſubſtance of bread and not Chriſts bodie (which were blaſphemie to affirme) that is ſo caſt out. <q>Cyprian ſaith:<note place="margin">De vnctione Chriſmatis.</note> 
                  <hi>Dedit dominus noſter &amp;c.</hi> Our Lord at the table whereat he did parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate his laſt feaſt with his diſciples, gaue with his own hands bread &amp; wine, but vpon the croſſe he gaue his bodie to be wounded by the hands of the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecr. diſt. 2. qui mandu.</note> Auguſtine alſo ſaith: <hi>Quod videtur panis eſt &amp;c.</hi> That which is ſéene is bread, and the cuppe which our eies alſo do ſhew vnto vs &amp;c.</q> He ſaith it is bread, and not ſéemeth or appeareth to be bread.<note place="margin">Auguſt. in pſal. 98.</note> And in another place: <hi>Spiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter intelligite quod loquutus ſum. Nen hoc corpus quod videtis manducaturi eſtis &amp;c. .i.</hi> Spiritually vnderſtand that which I haue ſpoken. You ſhall not eate this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die which you ſée, nor drinke that blood, which they ſhall ſhead that crucifie mée. I commend vnto you a certaine ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which being ſpiritually vnderſtood ſhall quicken you. For although it muſt
<pb facs="tcp:9998:29"/> of neceſſity be viſiblie celebrated, yet it muſt inuiſibly be vnderſtood. Iuſtinus Martyr ſaith:<note place="margin">Iuſtinus Apol. 2 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Pag. 162.</note> that the ſubſtance of the ſacrament is turned into vs, and that thereby our fleſh and blood is nouriſhed. But it were a great abſurdity to ſay that our fleſh and blood is nouriſhed of Chriſts bodie and blood conuerted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. Therefore it is bread &amp; wine which be turned into vs, and whereby we are nouriſhed. By theſe places that I alledge no more it is as cleare as the ſunne that the godly fathers did nothing at all doubt of this our doctrin, but were of this iudgement, that the ſubſtance of bread and wine remaine ſtill in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. Now it followeth that I ſhew that this doctrine of the Papiſts is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the nature of a ſacrament, the which ſufficiently appeareth, by that which is before declared, for I ſhewed that a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t conſiſteth of two things an earthly and an heauenly the ſigne &amp; the thing ſignified, and that there muſt be a ſimilitude and agréement betwéene theſe two, or elſe (as I alledged out of Auguſtine) it can be no ſacrament,<note place="margin">Epiſ. 13.</note> for as bread and wine, féede, ſtrengthen, and comfort mans heart and bodie: ſo
<pb facs="tcp:9998:30"/> Chriſts bodie and blood, féed, ſtrengthen, and comfort our ſoules. Now if there be no bread nor wine, then it cannot féede, ſtrengthen, and comfort vs, and then it hath no ſimilitude and agréement with Chriſts bodie and blood, and ſo by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent (according to Auguſtines iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) it is no ſacrament. And thus the Papiſts ſtriuing through blinde igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, to take bread and wine from the ſacrament, do indéede take away the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament it ſelf, and ſo haue nothing but an Idole of their owne. Now it remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that I proue it to be contrarie to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgement of our ſenſes, the which née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no proofe: for who knoweth not, that to the eie it is bread and wine, to the taſte it is breade and wine, to the féeling and ſmelling it is breade and wine, and not the body &amp; blood of Chriſt. Therefore I conclude that it is bread &amp; wine. But here me thinke I heare ſome Papiſts exclaiming and ſaying, phy for ſhame, that you ſhould vſe ſuch Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to meaſure theſe myſteries by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> externall iudgement of our ſenſes. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere that I am nothing at al aſhamed of this argument, ſéeing that the beſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputer that euer was in the world, and
<pb facs="tcp:9998:30"/> that moſt mightily maintained y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth, and confounded his aduerſaries vſed the ſame, which was neither Chriſippus nor Ariſtotle, but Ieſus Chriſt the ſon of God, for when he appeared after his reſurrection to his diſciples, and they were abaſhed &amp; affraid,<note place="margin">Luke. 24 37. Ioh. 20.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſuppoſing they had ſéene a ſpirit, he ſaid vnto them, why are ye troubled? &amp; wherefore do doubts ariſe in your hearts?<note place="margin">17.</note> behold my hands &amp; my féete: for it is I my ſelf: <hi>Handle me and ſee:</hi> for a ſpirit hath not fleſh and bones as yee ſée me haue. Here we ſée that our ſauiour proueth by ſéeing and handling, his bodie to be no ſpirit, but a true bodie. The ſame reaſon doth Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian vſe, againſt that monſter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of whom I before ſpake: his words be theſe: <hi>Hic primum manus ei iniectas animaduertens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 4. adue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Martionem.</note> 
               <hi>neceſſe habeo iam de ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia eius corporali prefinire, quòd non poſsit phantaſma credi, qui contactum &amp; quidem violentia plenum detentus &amp; cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus &amp; ad precipitium vſque protractus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſerit. i.</hi> I conſidering that heere firſt hands were laid vpon him (Chriſt) I muſt of neceſſitie determine of his Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ſubſtance,<note place="margin">Luk. 4.</note> that he cannot bée
<pb facs="tcp:9998:31"/> thought to be a ſpirit or ghoſt, who being detained, and kept, and brought euen vnto the ſteypie place ſuffered himſelfe ſo violently to be handled, and to that purpoſe immediatly after alledgeth a verſe of Lucretius. <hi>Tangere enim &amp; tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi niſi corpus nulla poteſt res. i.</hi> Nothing can touch and be touched but a bodie. Therfore either our ſauiour Chriſt and Tertullian vſed a reaſon that hath no reaſon, which I truſt our aduerſaries will not ſay, or elſe our reaſon is verie ſtrong, that trie it by touching, ſéeing, &amp; taſting and it will appeare to be bread. And ſo much the ſtronger is this reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for that our ſaid aduerſaries ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſhew one example in all the ſcriptures, where one ſubſtance by Gods mighty power being changed into an other, there was not alſo an outward change of the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and properties thereof, to be deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the outward ſenſes. As when Moſes rodde was chaunged into a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,<note place="margin">Exod. 4.3.</note> it was not onely in ſubſtance, but alſo in externall ſhew a ſerpent, ſo that Moſes for feare fled from it.<note place="margin">Exod. 7.21.</note> When the water in Egypt was turned into blood, it was blood not onely in ſubſtance, but
<pb facs="tcp:9998:31"/> alſo in external appearance to the eye &amp; taſt, ſo that the Egyptians could not drinke of it.<note place="margin">Iohn. 2.9.</note> When our ſauiour Chriſt had in Cana of Galile turned the water into wine, the gouernour of the feaſt as ſoone as he taſted it, perceiued it to be verie good wine. And therefore this ſhould ſéeme to be very ſtraunge, that here ſhould be ſuch a chaunge or tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation (as they terme it) of one thing into another, and no alteration of any outward qualities to be diſcerned by the iudgement of the ſenſes. This were contrarie to Gods working in all other myracles. So that it is hereby eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that this is no ſuch myracle as they imagine, as alſo Auguſtine flatly affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in his third Booke and <hi>10.</hi> Chapt. of the Trinitie.<note place="margin">Aug. de mirab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> libus Script.</note> And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Auguſtine writing a particuler booke of all the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles in the ſcriptures, maketh no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all hereof: by theſe reaſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alledged it doth I truſt plainely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that the ſubſtance of bread &amp; wine in the ſacrament do remaine and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue: well then ſay the Papiſts it is but bread, and we may receiue it as onely a péece of bread? Nay not ſo, we teach and
<pb facs="tcp:9998:32"/> beléeue,<note place="margin">Iuſtinus Apog. 2 Ireneus lib. 4. cap. 34.</note> that it is not to compted nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued as common bread and wine, but a ſacrament of Ieſus Chriſt, a ſeale of Gods promiſes, yea and an effectual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of Gods grace, whereby Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt with his righteouſnes and al other benefits of his paſſion is offred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. And to make this matter more plaine by an example: euen as the Queenes maieſties ſeale ioyned to her Letters pattents, is in ſubſtance waxe ſtil, but yet not to be reputed as commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> waxe, but to be reuerenced as her maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſeale, and it and the ſaid Letters pattents to the which it is ioyned carry a power with them, and be effectual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to conuey neuer ſo great a thing to vs, yea euen to bring vs pardon for our life, being condemned to die: euen ſo the promiſes of God and the ſacraments annexed as ſeales thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to be meanes to conueigh Ieſus Chriſt vnto vs, and with him forgiuenes of all our ſinnes, and a free pardon from eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal death which we haue deſerued. And therefore although bread and wine doe there remaine, as the ſubſtance of water doth in Baptiſme (the other ſacrament
<pb facs="tcp:9998:32"/> and ſeal of Gods promiſe) continue: yet it is very reuerently to be receiued, as a Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Ieſus Chriſt, and a pledge of our ſaluation in him. Now laſtly that this doctrine of theirs draweth with it diuerſe abſurdities, hath partly alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die appeared. As for to ſay, that they breake not the ſubſtance of breade, but either onely accidences, or Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is an abſurditie, to ſay that the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidences do hang in the aire, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſubiect, is, an abſurditie: or to ſay that they bee in Chriſtes bodie, is an other abſurdetie. To ſay that there is a conuerſion and chaunge of the ſubſtance, and none of the external qualities and properties is an abſurdity and contrarie to all other myracles in the Scriptures as before is declared. But of other abſurdities which followe this abſurd doctrine of tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I will hereafter by Gods grace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate.</p>
            <p>Now I come to the ſecond error of the Papiſts, concerning the preſence of the verie reall and naturall bodie of Ieſus Chriſt, vnder thoſe accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces and formes of bread and wine, which I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme
<pb facs="tcp:9998:33"/> to be contrarie to the Articles of our faith, to the holy ſcriptures, to the ſayings of the ancient fathers, and that it bringeth with it ſundrie abſurdities. Firſt we beleeue and confeſſe in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of our faith, that Chriſt is aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſitteth at the right hand of God, &amp; from thence ſhall come againe to iudge the quicke and the dead.<note place="margin">Matth. 26.11.</note> So in the ſcriptures our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith the poore ye ſhal haue alwaies with you but me ye ſhall not haue alwaies. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, I came out from the father, and came into the world:<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.28.</note> Againe, I leaue the world and go to the father. Alſo he ſaith,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.11.</note> and now <hi>I am no more in the world,</hi> but theſe are in the world: Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alſo ſaith,<note place="margin">Actes. 3.21.</note> that the heauen muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine him, vntill that all things be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored. But here the Papiſts haue an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhift, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt is not here now vpon earth in that viſible maner, that he was then. This is as much as if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould ſay: I wil leaue this houſe, I wil abide no more in this houſe, and yet he hideth himſelfe vnder ſome hangings that he is not ſeene: doth that man ſay truely? or is he not therefore in the houſe? yea but
<pb facs="tcp:9998:33"/> they replie &amp; ſay that our Sauiour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſaid.<note place="margin">Matth. 28.</note> Behold I am with you to the end of the world. I anſwere that our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt by his diuine nature and godhead is with vs to preſerue, direct and comfort vs: but in reſpect of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and humane nature which he took of the bleſſed virgin, he is not nowe vppon earth. And therefore our Sauiour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf warneth vs to beware and take héed of ſuch falſe Prophets as ſay heere is Chriſt, or there is Chriſt,<note place="margin">Matth. 24.23.</note> he is in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, or in ſecreat places,<note place="margin">26.</note> and bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs beleeue them not, for (ſaith he) as the lightning commeth out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eaſt and appeareth in the Weſt,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> ſo ſhall alſo the comming of the ſonne of man be. As though he ſhould ſay, my comming ſhal not be ſecreat and inuiſible vnder the formes of bread and wine, but euen as the lightning is viſible and terrible to the world, ſo ſhall my comming bée, which then ſhalbe when I ſhall come in maieſtie, power, and glory to iudge the quicke and the dead, vpon which words S. Hierome writeth thus:<note place="margin">Hierom. in Matth. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Stultum eſt itaque eum in paruo loco vel abſcondito quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, qui totius mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di lumen ſit .i.</hi> It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:9998:34"/> a fooliſh thing to ſéek him in a ſmall ſecreat place (ſuch as is a pix) who is the light of the whole world. Chriſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in reſpect of his humanitie and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, is not to be ſought or found vpon earth. But they replie that in as much as our ſauiour Chriſt is not onely man but alſo god, being Immanuel god with vs, and that theſe two natures being v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited in one perſon, &amp; make one Chriſt, therefore whereſoeuer is the one nature that is the deitie, there is the other viz. the humanitie. I anſwere that this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth not, for although I confeſſe that to be moſt true of the vniting of the two natures in one perſon: yet we muſt not with the heritike Eutiches confound thoſe two natures, but acknowledge the ſeueral properties apperteining to them to remaine diſtinct, and that they are to be diſtinguiſhed of vs.<note place="margin">Iohn. 14.28.</note> In this ſenſe Chriſt ſaid, The father is greater then I, the which is to be vnderſtood in reſpect of his humanitie: for in reſpect of his dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, he ſaith the father and I are one: and as S. Paul ſaith,<note place="margin">Philip. 2.6.</note> he thought it no rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery to be equal with God.<note place="margin">Mark. 13.32.</note> So in reſpect of his humanitie he confeſſeth himſelf to
<pb facs="tcp:9998:34"/> be ignorant of the day of iudgement, but in reſpect of his godhead he knoweth all things. In reſpect of his manhood hée was ſubiect to infirmities, as hunger,<note place="margin">Matth. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Iohn. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.</note> wearineſſe, yea and vnto death. but in reſpect of his deitie he was ſubiect to none of theſe, but was impaſſible, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall: So in reſpect of his manhood he was contained in place, and when hée was riſen, the Angel ſaid he is riſen and is not here, but in reſpect of his godhead, he is in all places,<note place="margin">1. King. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> the heauens of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s do not contein him. So I conclude that in reſpect of his humaine nature &amp; bodie as when he was in earth, he was not in heauen: ſo now being in heauen he is not vpon earth, and therefore in reſpect of his humain nature he ſaid, me ye ſhal not haue alwayes, I leaue the world, I am no more in the world: and in reſpect of his deitie he ſaid: behold I am with you to the end of the world. And yet I confeſſe that we may truely ſay that whole Ieſus Chriſt God and man is with vs to the end of the world, <hi>In vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate perſonae, non proprietate naturae.</hi> as S. Auguſtin ſaith, <hi>i.</hi> in vnitie of perſon, not in propriety of nature: for if we conſider
<pb facs="tcp:9998:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9998:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9998:36"/> perticulerly his humaine nature that is not with vs. This doctrine the ancient Fathers moſt plainely ſet forth, as Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine:<note place="margin">Auguſt. Epiſt. 57 ad Dardanum.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na enim perſona deus &amp; homo &amp;c. i.</hi> for he being God and man is one perſon, and booth is one Chriſt Ieſus, who is euery where in that he is God, but in heauen in that he is man. Againe <hi>Ille abſens eſt praeſentia corporis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 127.</note> 
               <hi>ſed preſens vigore maieſtatis .i.</hi> he is abſent in reſpect of the preſens of his bodie, but preſent by the power of his maieſty. And again: <hi>Surſum eſt dominus &amp;c. i.</hi> the Lord is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Ioan. tract. 30.</note> but alſo here is the Lord the truth. <q>For the body of the Lord, wherin he did riſe, can be but in one place, but his truth is diſperſed euery where. Againe: let good men alſo take this,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Ioan. tract. 50.</note> and not bée carefull:</q> for he ſpake of the preſence of his bodie. for as touching his maieſty, his prouidence, his ineffable and ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable grace, that is fulfilled which hée ſaid, behold I am with you alwaies to the end of the world: <q>But touching the fleſh which the word took to it, touching that, by which he was borne of the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, apprehended of the Iewes, crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon wood, taken from the croſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:9998:36"/> wrapped in clothes, laid in the ſepulchre reueiled in the reſurrection, ye ſhall not alwayes haue him with you. Why? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was conuerſant with his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <hi>40.</hi> dayes in reſpect of his bodely preſence, &amp; they waiting on him, ſeing him, but not following him, he aſcended into heauen, and is not here? for he is there, ſitting at the right hand of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and he is here, for he hath not left vs by the preſence of his maieſtie &amp;c.</q>
               <note place="margin">Contr. fauſtum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> lib. 20. cap. 11.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, Auguſtine ſaith: Chriſt accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his corporall preſence, could not be at once in the ſonne, in the moone,<note place="margin">Lib. 1. co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Eutic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> &amp; vpon the croſſe. <q>Vigilius a godly Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of Tridente and Martyr giueth moſt plaine witneſſe to this truth, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Nam vide myraculum, vide vtriuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que proprietatis myſterium &amp;c.</hi> for ſée a myracle, ſée the myſterie of the property of both the natures. The ſonne of God according to his humanitie is gone from vs according to his diuinitie he ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. Behold I am with you, alwayes to the end of the world: if he be with you, how doth he ſay, The day ſhal come when ye ſhall deſire to ſée one day of the ſonne of man, &amp; you ſhall not ſée it. But
<pb facs="tcp:9998:37"/> both he is with vs, &amp; he is not with you: for whom he hath left, and from whom he is departed in his humanitie, he hath not left nor forſaken by his deitie: for by the forme of a ſeruant, which he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from vs into heauen, he is abſent from vs, but by the forme of God, which doth not depart from vs, he is preſent in earth with vs: ſo he being one and the ſame, is both preſent with vs, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from vs. And againe the ſame Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilius ſaith,<note place="margin">Lib. 4. contr. Eutichen.</note> 
                  <hi>Deinde ſi verbi &amp; carnis &amp;c.</hi> Moreouer if there be one nature of the word and fleſh, how commeth it to paſſe, that the word being euerie where, the fleſh is not alſo founde to be euerie where, for when it was in the earth, it was not in heauen: and for that now it is in heauen, it is not in earth, and in ſo much it is not, that according to it, wée looke for Chriſt to come from heauen, whom according to the word, we beléeue to be with vs in the earth. Therefore according to your doctrine, either the <hi>word</hi> is conteined in place with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, or the fleſh is euery where with the word, ſeeing that one nature receiueth not in it ſelfe any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb facs="tcp:9998:37"/> and diuers.</q> Hitherto Vigilius, whereby we may ſée how néere the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ioine with that old heretical Abbot Eutiches condemned in the counſell of Calcidone, in confounding the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of both natures, and holding that Chriſts fleſh and body is at one inſtant both in heauen and earth and in infinit places of the earth. Therfore we are not to ſéeke our ſauiour Chriſt in earth, but we muſt be Eagles to ſoare vp by faith into heauen, and there to eat his fleſh &amp; drinke his blood. S. Paul exhorteth vs to ſeeke the things that be aboue,<note place="margin">Colloſſ. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of God: in which words he moueth vs to ſeeke the things that be there where Chriſt is, but Chriſt is aboue in heauen, therefore wée muſt ſeeke the thinges that bée aboue in heauen and not the thinges that be vppon earth. But if Chriſt bée vpon earth as the Papiſts teach, then either Paules reaſon is not good, or we may ſeeke the things that he vppon earth, which he doth in expreſſe words forbid vs. But I will proſecute this matter no further, onely I will lay forth certaine abſurdities that follow of
<pb facs="tcp:9998:38"/> this groſſe doctrine of Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If Chriſts real and natural bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy be there vnder thoſe formes of bread and wine as they teach, then we do with our mouthes receiue and eate the verie bodie of Chriſt, and drinke his blood, but this is not onely an abſurditie, but alſo wickedneſſe and impietie as S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine ſaith,<note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. 3. de doct. chriſt. cap. 16.</note> whoſe words are worthy wel to be marked and conſidered. He giuing rules how to vnderſtand the ſcriptures, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt others giueth this for one, <q>That if the ſcripture ſeeme either to command any thing that is euill and nought, or to forbid any thing that is good and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then it is not a proper ſpeach, but a figuratiue. The example that he brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth is this. Except ye eate the fleſh of the ſonne of man, and drinke his blood ye ſhall haue no life in you. He ſeemeth to commaund (ſaith he) a horrible and wicked thing. Therefore it is a figure, commaunding vs to communicate vpon the Lords paſſion, and ſweetly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably to hide vp in memory, that his fleſh was crucified and wounded for vs.</q> In which words S. Auguſtine not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:9998:38"/> condemneth, that groſſe and Caper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naicall eating and drinking of Chriſts fleſh and blood, which the Papiſts ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, but alſo ſheweth what it is to eat his fleſh and drinke his blood, euen faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to beleeue and acknowledge in our hearts, that his bodie was crucified and his blood ſhed vpon the croſſe for vs. But Pope Nicolas with the Romane coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell enforcing that excellent learned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Berengarius to recant, and denie the true doctrine which he had mainteyned, cauſed him to confeſſe (as appeareth in the Popes owne decrees) the very body of Chriſt in truth to be handled by the prieſts hands,<note place="margin">De conſec. diſt. 2. Ego Beringa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius manibus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerd. frangi, &amp; fidelium denti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus atteri.</note> and to be broken &amp; torne by the téeth of the faithful. The which is ſo abſurd and groſſe that the very bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous writer of the gloſſe vppon that place, giueth warning warely and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Beringarius words, or elſe we may fal into greater hereſie then he held.</p>
            <p>An other abſurditie is this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if Chriſt naturall bodie be in the ſacrament, then our ſauiour Chriſt did eat his owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, for that our ſauiour Chriſt did eate the ſacrament, doth appeare by theſe his
<pb facs="tcp:9998:39"/> words after ſupper. Verely I ſay vnto you,<note place="margin">Matth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.</note> I will not henceforth drinke anie more of the fruit of the vine &amp;c. And as our Sauiour vouchſafed to be baptized, that he might ſanctifie Baptiſme vnto vs, euen ſo he did receiue this ſacrament alſo, to ſanctifie it vnto vs, and thereby to aſſure vs the more of our communion &amp; fellowſhip with him.<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. in Mat. Homil. 83. de Conſecr. diſt. 2. cap. nec Moſes. Et gloſ. in cap. in Chriſto.</note> This both Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſtom doth flatly affirm, and the papiſts themſelues do not deny, but plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe in theſe rude rimes without reaſon. <hi>Rex ſedet in Coena turba cinctus dnodena. Se tenet in manibus, ſe cibat ipſe cibo. i.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The king ſitting at his ſupper with his xii. Apoſtles helde himſelfe in his hands, and fedde himſelfe with the meat of himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Now whether this be not an abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that our ſauiour Chriſt ſitting with his diſciples, did with his natural body, eate his naturall body, I will commit it to the conſcience and iudgement of the godly to conſider. And whether it muſt not hereof follow that he had too bodies, one an Actiue, that did eate, and another a paſſiue that was eaten.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> An other abſurditie hereof enſueth,
<pb facs="tcp:9998:39"/> that whereas the papiſts teach y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſts body is in the ſacrament, being impaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, mortall, and glorified, contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries muſt néeds be affirmed at one inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vpon Chriſts bodie: for his body where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſate at the table with his diſciples was viſible, but the body in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment inuiſible: that bodie was paſſible, this impaſſible: that ſubiect to death which ſhortly after died vpon the croſſe: this not ſubiect to death. Now it can no more be, that Chriſts body at one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, ſhould be viſible and inuiſible, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and impaſſible, ſubiect to death and not ſubiect to death: then it can be a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and no body. And therefore this is a foule abſurditie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Moreouer for Chriſts body to be at one inſtant in heauen and earth and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite places of the earth, is as I haue ſhewed, and proued before an abſurdity.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> And that Chriſts bodie ſhould bée in the Sacrament without any accidences of a body, as form, figure, le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, breadth, thickneſſe, is as I touched before an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurditie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> This doctrine bringeth an other ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity, which they maintain: that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="tcp:9998:40"/> men do eat the very body of Chriſt. Whereas Chriſt himſelfe ſaith:<note place="margin">Iohn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.54.</note> whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer eateth my fleſh and drinketh my blood,<note place="margin">56.</note> hath eternall life, and I will raiſe him vp at the laſt day. And againe, he that eateth my fleſh and drinketh my blood,<note place="margin">57.</note> dwelleth in me and I in him: hée that eateth me ſhal liue by me. But the wicked haue not eternall life, neither do they liue by Chriſt being deade in their ſinnes. Therefore the wicked do not eat Chriſts fleſh nor drink his blood. Auguſtine ſaith:<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Ioh. tract. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Huius rei ſacramentum id eſt vnitatis &amp;c.</hi> 
               <q>The ſacrament of this thing, that is of the vnitie of Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and blood is prepared in the Lords table, and receiued of the Lords table, in ſome places euery day, in ſome at certaine times, of ſome men to life, of ſome to deſtruction. But the thing it ſelfe wherof it is a ſacrament is deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to none, but life to euery one that is partaker of it. Again the ſame Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine ſaith:<note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. 21. de imitat. Dei cap. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Non dicendum eum manduca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re corpus Chriſti, qui in corpore non eſt Chriſti. i.</hi> we muſt not ſay that he doth eate the body of Chriſt, who is not in the body of Chriſt. And againe in the
<pb facs="tcp:9998:40"/> ſame place.<note place="margin">Idem ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Nec iſti ergo dicendi ſunt manducare corpus Chriſti, quoniam nec in membris computandi ſunt Chriſti &amp;c.</hi> Therefore they are not to be ſaid to eat the bodie of Chriſt, becauſe they are not to be counted among the members of Chriſt, for not to ſpeake of other things they cannot at one time be the members of Chriſt and the members of a harlot. Origene ſaith: <hi>Eſt verus cibus. i.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Orig. in Matth. 15.</note> that is the true meate, which no wicked man can eate: for if a wicked man could eat the body of Chriſt, it would not be wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, He that eateth this bread ſhall liue for euer. Theſe places I do alledge to confute not onely this abſurd aſſertion, but alſo that groſſe doctrine of tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation:</q> for if the bread be ſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiated into Chriſts body (then the wicked do eate Chriſts body: if the wicked do not eat Chriſts body, (as by the proofes before alledged doth plainely appeare) then is there no ſuch tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation nor carnall preſence as they vainely imagine, and falſely affirme for to be. But heere alſo they want not a ſhift, which is, that the wicked doe eate Chriſts fleſh and drink his blood but not
<pb facs="tcp:9998:41"/> worthily. But I would haue them to proue that a man may eate Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die vnworthely. In déede I confeſſe that the wicked may vnworthely eat of this bread &amp; drink of this cuppe of the Lords,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.27.</note> and be guilty of the bodie and blood of Chriſt, as S. Paul ſaith, becauſe that through infidelitie they do reiect Ieſus Chriſt offred therby. But that the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and reprobate be either worthely or vnworthely partakers of Ieſus Chriſt, that I do deny. Yet to proue this ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe aſſertion ſee how they be not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med wilfully to corrupt the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Titul. 21. Arti. 1. de ſumpt. Euch.</note>Bunderius a lying and falſe Frier, is not abaſhed thus to alledge S. Paules place which euen now I brought forth: <hi>Multi enim indigne accipiunt de quibus ait Apoſtolus: Qui manducat carnem, &amp; bibit calicem domini indigne iuditium ſibi manducat &amp; bibit. i.</hi> For many do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthely receiue of whom the Apoſtle ſpeaketh. He that eateth the fleſh and drinketh the cuppe of the Lord vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely, eateth &amp; drinketh his owne dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Heere this deceitfull Frier for <hi>panem</hi> the bread putteth <hi>carnem</hi> the fleſh
<pb facs="tcp:9998:41"/> that whereas the Apoſtle ſaith, he that eateth this bread, and drinketh this cup &amp;c. He maketh him to ſay, he that eateth the fleſh and drinketh the cuppe of the Lord vnworthely: wherein you ſée how he altereth S. Pauls words and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the place. But no maruell for ſuch ſhameleſſe aſſertions, and corrupt doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin, cannot be defended without ſhame leſſe corrupting of the holy Scriptures. But they will ſay, the ſenſe and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is all one: for he that eateth that bread, eateth Chriſts body. But that is the queſtion, and therefore they vſe a deceitfull Argument called <hi>petitio princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pii,</hi> taking that for graunted which is in queſtion and is denied: for the bread is one thing, Chriſts bodie an other: And although we are not to ſeperate Chriſt from the ſacrament, yet we ought not to confound them, but to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene them: for euen as the godly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did teach touching the two na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the deitie and humanity in our Sauiour Chriſt, that they are neither to be diſtracted a ſunder and ſeperated, as did Neſtorius, nor the properties of them to be confounded, as did Eutiches:
<pb facs="tcp:9998:42"/> but the ſaid properties are to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed. Euen ſo are we to deale in this matter of the ſacrament, concerning the ſigne and thing ſignified, that neither they are to be diſtracted a ſunder, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided: nor to be confounded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ogether, but to be diſtinguiſhed. The ſign which is the bread and wine, are things viſible and corruptible which wil in ſhort time putrifie: Ieſus Chriſt the thing ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is to our outward eyes inuiſible and is incorruptible. The bread and wine are vpon earth: Ieſus Chriſt is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen at the right hand of God. The bread &amp; wine are receiued with our mouthes, broken with our téeth, and féede our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: Ieſus Chriſt is <hi>fide digerendus</hi> ſaith Tertullian<note place="margin">Tertull. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrect. carnis.</note> receiued and eaten by faith, &amp; féedeth our ſoules to liue to God eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally: The bread and wine are receiued of all both faithfull and vnfaithfull, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wicked. Ieſus Chriſt is onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of them who be faithful,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.</note> in whoſe hearts he dwelleth by faith. They that do eate the bread and wine do die, not onely this outward death, but alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny die eternally:<note place="margin">Iohn. 9.51.</note> but he that eateth this bread that came downe from heauen
<pb facs="tcp:9998:42"/> which is Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe ſhal liue for euer. Thus a difference is to be put betwéene the externall ſacrament, and Ieſus Chriſt of whom it is a Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And yet we muſt not diſtract &amp; ſeperate altogether Ieſus Chriſt from the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but beléeue that he is truely offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to all, and effectually receiued of thoſe that be gods children, and haue a true faith, which is the very mouth of the ſoule, whereby they eate his fleſh &amp; drinke his blood, as Chriſt ſaith:<note place="margin">Iohn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.35.</note> I am the bread of life, he that commeth to me ſhall neuer hunger, and he that belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in me ſhall neuer thirſt.</p>
            <p>Now I will onely ſhew briefly the vncertainty of this doctrin of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation,<note place="margin">Lib. 4. diſt. 11. cap. Si autem.</note> and ſo I will end this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. Peter Lombard the maſter of the ſentences writeth thus: <q>
                  <hi>Si autem quaeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur qualis ſit illa conuerſio an formalis an ſubſtantialis, vel alterius generis, definire no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſufficio: formalem tamen non eſſe cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſco quia ſpecies quae ante fuerant rema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. i.</hi> If it be aſked what kinde of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion that is, whether formal or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall, or of any other kind I am not able to define. But yet I know, that it
<pb facs="tcp:9998:43"/> is not a formal conuerſion, becauſe that the formes and ſhewes which were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do ſtill remaine. Afterward he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: ſome think that it is a ſubſtantiall conuerſion, ſaying that one ſubſtance is ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted into an other ſubſtance, that the one is eſſentially made the other, to the which ſenſe the fore alledged autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities do ſéeme to conſent. But ſome do not graunt that the ſubſtance of bread, is at any time made the fleſh of Chriſt. Others be graunt, that that which was bread or wine, after conſecration is the body and blood of Chriſt: Some doe ſay thus, that that conuerſion is ſo to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode, that vnder thoſe accidences, vnder which before was the ſubſtance of bread and wine, after conſecration is the ſubſtance of the body &amp; blood:</q> but others haue thought that the ſubſtance of bread and wine doe there remaine, and that there alſo is the body and blood of Chriſt. Hitherto the maſter of all the Popiſh ſchoolemen, whoſe booke of Sentences was of ſuch credite and autority with them that it was more read &amp; expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded then the holy bible. Whereby wée may plainely ſée how vncertaine this
<pb facs="tcp:9998:43"/> their doctrine is, and what diuers opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons haue bene of it. So Gabriel Byell<note place="margin">Gab. Biell in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſit. Canonis Miſſae lect. 40.</note> an other great ſcholeman writeth thus: <hi>Quomodo ibi ſit Chriſti corpus, an per con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſionem alicuius in ipſum an ſine conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one incipiat enim corpus Chriſti cum pane, manentibus ſubſtantia &amp; accidentibus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, non inuenitur expreſſum in canone Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliae. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde de hoc antiquitus fuerunt diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae opiniones .i.</hi> 
               <q>How the body of Chriſt is there, whether by conuerſion of ſome thing into it, or without conuerſion, there beginne to the body of Chriſt with the bread, the ſubſtance and accidences of the breade remaining ſtill, it is not <hi>found expreſſed in the canon of the bible.</hi> Whereupon in old time there were diuers opinions hereof.</q> And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he rehearſeth foure. Beſides this, what if Iohn Fiſher biſhop of Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, a great patrone of the Pope and his doctrine, doe flatly confeſſe that this preſence of Chriſts body and blood in the ſacrament cannot be proued by the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.<note place="margin">Ioh. Roffenſ. Epiſc. in defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Regiae aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis cont. cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuit. Babiloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam M. Lutheri N. 8. &amp; O.</note> Whoſe words be theſe, <hi>Hactenus Mattheus &amp;c.</hi> 
               <q>Hitherto Matthew who onely maketh mention of the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament: neither is there any word here
<pb facs="tcp:9998:44"/> ſet downe, whereby it may be prooued that in our maſſe, there is made a true preſence of Chriſts bodie and blood: for although Chriſt made of the breade his fleſh, and of the wine his blood, it doth not therefore follow, that we by vertue of any word here ſet downe, can doe the like, when we attempt the ſame. Again he ſaith: <hi>Non poteſt per vllam ſcripturam probari &amp;c.</hi> It cannot be proued by any ſcripture, that either a layman, or prieſt as often as he attempteth the ſame, can in like manner make of bread and wine the bodie and blood of Chriſt, as Chriſt himſelfe made, ſéeing this is not contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſcriptures. And again he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth this matter thus:<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Ex iis opinor &amp;c.</hi> By theſe things I ſuppoſe euery man perceiueth that the certenty of this matter depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth not ſo much of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, as of the vſe and cuſtome, which ſo many ages hath bene commended vnto vs from the verie firſt fathers.</q> Héere by the iudgement of Biſhop Fiſher, this doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all preſence, dependeth not ſo much vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Goſpel, as vpon cuſtome: &amp; that it cannot be proued by the Scriptures:
<pb facs="tcp:9998:44"/> whereby we may ſée how vncertaine it is. So that we may ſay with Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian: <hi>Nihil de eo conſtat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. de carne Chriſti.</note> 
               <hi>quia Scriptura non exhibet .i.</hi> We know nothing thereof, becauſe the Scripture doth not ſhew it. And againe:<note place="margin">Lib. de mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamia.</note> 
               <hi>Negat ſcriptura quod non notat .i.</hi> The ſcripture doth deny that, which it doth not expreſſe: wherefore let vs forſake this doubtful doctrine, yea this erronious, abſurd and falſe doctrin, and let vs imbrace the truth before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared: let vs not ſéeke Chriſt here vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, but let vs lift vp our hearts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen, &amp; there by faith eate Chriſts bleſſed body that was offred, and drinke his precious blood ſhedde vpon the croſſe for vs, to feede and nouriſh our ſoules to eternal life, which is not to be done car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, but ſpiritually, yet truely and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually. Now let vs prepare our ſelues to come reuerently and worthely to this holy ſacrament, the which that we may do: we ought as S. Paul exhorteth vs,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> to proue and examine our ſelues, and ſo to eat of this bread &amp; drink of this cuppe for he that eateth this bread, and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this cup of the Lord vnworthely, eateth and drinketh his owne damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb facs="tcp:9998:45"/> We are therefore, not ſo much to examine others, which by confeſſions prieſts did in popery, as to try our ſelues &amp; to cal our ſelues to account before god. Firſt we muſt examine our own hearts, whether we imbrace and beléeue in our hearts the true doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctified vnto vs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures, &amp; ſealed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood of Chriſt: &amp; chiefly whether we reſt onely vpon the righteouſneſſe of Ieſus Chriſt, and that we ſéeke our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation onely in him, who is giuen of God,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30.</note> to be vnto vs wiſedome, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſanctification and redemption, that he that reioyceth, may reioyce in the Lord. If we doe not vnfainedly yeld to this true doctrine, it is impoſſible, that we can be worthy receiuers of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament which (as I haue declared) is ordained and giuen vnto vs to ſeale and confirme the ſaid true doctrin of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation onely by Ieſus Chriſt crucified, vnto our hearts and conſciences. And therefore if any that do not beléeue with his heart, and confeſſe with his mouth this holy and heauenly doctrine, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill froſen in the dregges of wicked ſuperſtition and deceiuable errour, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:9998:45"/> ſome part of ſaluation in mens me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and in their owne works, come to receiue this holy myſtery and ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not worthely receiue it, but doth moſt wickedly abuſe it. Doing in like ſort, as if a man ſhould put her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſeale, to ſuch a writing as ſhe neuer allowed, graunted, nor commaunded, but is directly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to her wil &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, he that ſo vſeth her ſeale, abuſeth her maieſty, is a traitour, and deſerueth to be hanged: euen ſo theſe men belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing erronious and falſe doctrine, ſuch as hath no warrant of Gods word, and is iniurious to the death and paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God, whereof this Sacrament is a ſeale: in receiuing it doe horribly abuſe it, in making it a ſeale of their damnable doctrine, and bée traitors to Ieſus Chriſt: and vnleſſe God in mercy graunt them repentance will hang in hell for it. Therefore ſuch as profeſſe popery, or any other wicked hereſie, and will not reny and forſake to ſinne, are not to be admitted to receiue this ſacrament,<note place="margin">Exod. 11.43.</note> for if no ſtranger might receiue the paſſeouer: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch as be not onely ſtraungers, but alſo enemies to
<pb facs="tcp:9998:46"/> the trueth, are not to receiue this our paſſeouer, which is a ſacrament of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, by whom we haue true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance from eternall deſtruction and damnation. They are therefore firſt to be inſtructed diligently in the truth, the which if they ſtubbernly withſtand, they ought ſeuerely by the magiſtrate to bée puniſhed, yea and generally al that are to be receiued to communicate of this holy ſacrament are firſt to be catechiſed and inſtructed in the true doctrine of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and are to be taught, what this ſacrament is, to what end it was ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and what comfort, and ſpirituall profit they are to receiue by it.<note place="margin">Eod. 12.26.</note> So God commaunded the Iſraelits to inſtruct their children in the doctrine of the paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, &amp; to teach them the cauſes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was ordeined, and appointed by God. And we reade that when Ioſiah did keepe that great paſſeouer,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Paralip. 35.6.</note> he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the Prieſts both to ſanctifie themſelues, &amp; to prepare their brethren, that they might do according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of the Lord by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hand of Moſes. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ought priuatly to teach their children, &amp; miniſters ſhould pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely
<pb facs="tcp:9998:46"/> inſtruct the people in all true doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and diligently prepare them, that they come worthely to the receiuing of this holy ſacrament. But theſe things are in a manner vtterly neglected, for parents haue no care nor conſcience of doing this duty which the Lord layeth vpon them, yea moſt be ſo blind and ſo ignorant themſelues in gods truth, that they be neither able to inſtruct them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, nor to teach others. Miniſters for the moſt part neither preach, nor Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe the people, but admit al hand ouer head to this holy ſacrament, where by it is greatly profaned and abuſed. Some thinke it ynough ſomtimes to preach, but they neither catechiſe and inſtruct the people in the grounds, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of religion, nor priuatly examine &amp; prepare them to the worthy communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating of this holy myſterie and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And therefore the people come ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly and without knowledge vnto it, without the which the mind of man cannot be good as Salomon ſaith:<note place="margin">Prouerb. 19.2.</note> and ſo moſt wickedly abuſe it, and kindle gods wrath againſt them for it: Let therfore parents do this duetie, which God laieth
<pb facs="tcp:9998:47"/> vpon them in teaching their children &amp; families the true knowledge of god, and the right vſe of this ſacrament. Let mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters both publikely preach Chriſts Goſpel, and alſo perticularly catechiſe and inſtruct their people in the doctrine of ſaluation, and namely of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they may reuerently &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely for the ſtrengthening of their faith &amp; comfort of their conſciences receiue it.</p>
            <p>Moreouer euery man that commeth to the lords table muſt examine his own heart, whether he féele the ſame touched with true repentance, and an effectuall remorſe for his manifold and haynous ſinnes commited againſt Gods maieſty, for as the Iſraelits were with bitter herbs to eat their paſſeouer:<note place="margin">Exod. 12.8.</note> ſo we ought to receiue this holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſts body and blood with bitter repentance for our manifold iniquities, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly pricked in conſcience, that wée haue ſo grieuouſly offended our grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God, in doing ſuch wicked things as he forbiddeth, and not doing thoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things that he commaundeth vs, or not doing them in that pure ſincere ſort that he requireth of vs.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9998:47"/>
            <p>This true repentance muſt bring with it, a true amendment and reformation of life, in forſaking ſuch ſins as we haue heretofore committed, and in indeuoring diligently to do thoſe things, that wée know to be good acceptable before God our Sauiour.<note place="margin">Iames. 5.12.</note> He that hath ben a ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer muſt ſweare no more, but let his ſpeach be yea yea, nay nay, leſt he fall into condemnation, and he muſt vſe his tongue not to blaſpheme, but to glorifie Gods name, and to praiſe him for his mercies euery morning renewed vnto him.<note place="margin">Lament. 3.23.</note> If any haue béene a prophanour of God Sabboth, a neglecter of gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and a contemner of his word: hée muſt forſake theſe ſinnes, he muſt ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Sabboth day, and conſecrate it as glorious to the Lord, not doing his own wayes, nor ſéeking his owne will,<note place="margin">Iſai. 58.13.</note> nor ſpeaking a vaine word, he muſt careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerue God with a pure conſcience, earneſtly loue his holy word, and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger after it, as his daily foode. He that hath ben an adulterer or fornicator muſt flée and forſake this filthy ſinne,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 4.4.</note> &amp; kéepe the veſſell of his body and ſoule in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and honour not in the luſts of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence
<pb facs="tcp:9998:48"/> as do the Gentiles that know not God. And if any come to this holy table like a filthy dogge before he haue bewailed vnfainedly this his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and if it be open, before he haue publikely ſhewed true tokens of his true repentance, and reconciled himſelf to the Church of God, he treadeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his filthy féete y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood of Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God, and eateth and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his owne damnation. Thoſe that haue beene dronkards, ought to forſake this beaſtlineſſe, and liue ſoberly and temperately in Gods feare, or elſe they in comming to this ſacrament prouoke Gods anger and indignation againſt them, and ſo receiue it to their deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But it is lamentable to ſée what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite numbers of whoremongers adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, inceſtious perſons, drunkards, &amp; ſuch other filthy ſwine, without any ſigne of repentance or ſatiſfaction to the Church of God by them offended, doe come and be receiued to the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating of this holy ſacrament.</p>
            <p>Laſtly we ought to examine our ſelues whether we liue in Chriſtian
<pb facs="tcp:9998:48"/> loue and charitie one with an other without which,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.1.</note> though we ſpeake with the mouth of men and angels and could moue mountaines, and did giue all our goods to the poore, yea and our bodies to be burned we be nothing, and without it, we can do nothing, that may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable before God, as our Sauiour Chriſt teacheth vs in theſe words. If thou bring the gift or oblation to the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.24.</note> and there remember that thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath ought againſt thée, leaue there thine offring before the alter, and goe thy way: firſt be reconciled to thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and then come and offer thy gift. Our Sauiour Chriſt here ſpeaking of the alter and oblations that were in the old law, doth teach vs, that we can do nothing acceptable to God, vnleſſe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be truely reconciled to our brethren, and do ſincerely loue them, euen as we deſire God in Ieſus Chriſt to loue vs. Therefore if we liue not in true bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue and charitie one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we cannot come worthely to this holy ſupper of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: for it is a ſacrament of vnitie as Saint Paul ſaith, we that are many,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.17.</note> are one
<pb facs="tcp:9998:49"/> bread &amp; one body, becauſe we al are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of one bread. For euen as we al eate of one bread, and drinke of one cup, ſo we declare and acknowledge thereby that we be all one in Chriſt Ieſus, all members of one myſticall body, and all lynked together in brotherly loue one with another. And as the bread is made of many graines knoden togither, euen ſo we ought all to be knit together in a holy profeſſion of one truth, and in bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly ſincere loue one to another, which muſt bring forth her fruits in humbling our ſelues one to another in the feare of God, in helping, comforting and relée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing one another &amp;c. But lamentable it is to ſée how cold Chriſtian charitie is waxen, and how rare it is among men. Al men ſéeke themſelues, and their own priuat profit, and not the good and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of their brethren: we diſpiſe and diſdaine one another: we ſéeke to exalt and aduance our ſelues one aboue an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: by vſury, bribery, extorſion, and oppreſſion we pinch, bite, yea and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour one an other. If theſe be our fruits, if thus we leade our liues, and yet come to communicate on this holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,
<pb facs="tcp:9998:49"/> we prouoke gods fearefull vengeance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, fearefully for to plague vs. So Paul ſheweth, that for the abuſing of this ſacrament at Corinth,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.30.</note> God had ſo ſtriken them, that many were dead, and many weak and ſicke among them. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I conſider how horribly this holy Sacrament is abuſed among vs, how this pearle is caſt before ſwine, and miniſtred to all, without making any difference betwéene the cleane and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, how ignorantly, vnreuerently and profanely it is receiued, I cannot but ſtand in terrour and horrour of gods fearefull plagues to come vpon vs, euen to the depriuing vs, of the word of life, the Goſpel of our ſaluation, and of this pretious pledge of our Redemption by Ieſus Chriſt. Let vs therefore deare brethren, iudge our ſelues, that we bee not iudged of the Lord our God, but let vs humble our ſelues vnder his mighty hand, let vs truely turne vnto him by vnfeined repentance, and amendment of life. Let vs with all reuerence come to this holy feaſt, vnfeinedly confeſſing our ſinnes with an inward féeling of them, &amp; remorſe of conſcience for them,
<pb facs="tcp:9998:50"/> &amp; truly truſting in gods mercy through Ieſus Chriſt, who came into this world to ſaue vs ſinners:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.15. 2. Cor. 8.9. Philip. 2.7.</note> who became poore to inrich vs: tooke vpon him the ſhape of a ſeruant to purchaſe eternal fréedome, and libertie to vs: ſubmitted himſelf to ſhame,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.13.15.</note> to procure euerlaſting glorie to vs: tooke vpon him the curſe, to obtaine the bleſſing of God for vs: finally ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red death to giue eternall life vnto vs. Thus when we come to receiue this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, let vs thus declare the death of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; acknowledge with heart and mouth, that the life wée now liue in the fleſh,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> we liue by the faith of the ſonne of God, who hath loued vs, and giuen himſelfe for vs. This is our worthy receiuing of this holy myſterie, euen effectually from our hearts to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our owne vnworthineſſe, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to hunger for the righteouſneſſe of Ieſus Chriſt, which onely is able to diſcharge our vnrighteouſneſſe. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we do vnfainedly confeſſe, our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe and wickedneſſe, and (not with a perfect faith, which no where is to be found, and which if we had, wée ſhould haue no ſuch néede of this ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:9998:50"/> which is ordeyned to ſtrengthen our faith and to be as it were a prop to vphold it) but with an vnfaigned faith (as the Apoſtle termeth it) come vnto Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.5.</note> lay our ſins vpon him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue that he hath made peace by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood of his croſſe,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 1.20.</note> &amp; that by his ſtripes we be healed, if we do truly amend our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full liues,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.24. 2. Pet. 1.4.</note> féeling the corruption that is in the world through luſt, and purelie ſerue God with good conſciences. And finally do reconcile our ſelues one to an other, and liue in brotherly loue and Chriſtian charitie one with an other: in comming to this ſacrament, we ſhall not onely licke the rocke, but alſo ſucke the hony and Oile out of the ſame as S. Cyprian ſaith:<note place="margin">Serm. de Caen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Domini.</note> we ſhall not onely eate <hi>Panem domini,</hi> the bread of the Lord as Iudas did:<note place="margin">Auguſt. in I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hn tract. 59.</note> but alſo <hi>Panem Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum,</hi> that bread which is the Lord, as the other diſciples of our ſauiour Chriſt did: we ſhall not onely receiue theſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible elements of bread and wine, but alſo we ſhal eat Chriſts fleſh and drinke his blood,<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.56.</note> he ſhall dwell in vs and we in him, and ſhall hereby more and more grow vp in him, and be more and more
<pb facs="tcp:9998:51"/> aſſured of our ſaluation in him. Theſe things the father of all mercie worke in vs, and continually increaſe in vs, to his owne glorie, and our eternall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and ſaluation through Ieſus Chriſt our onely ſauiour &amp; redéemer, to whom with the Father &amp; the holy Ghoſt, be all praiſe, laud, and glorie now and for euer Amen.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>HOSEA. 14.10.</bibl>
               <p>Who is wiſe, and he ſhall vnderſtand theſe things? and prudent and he ſhall know them? for the wayes of the Lord are vpright: and the iuſt ſhal walke in them: but the wicked ſhall fall therein.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDON. <hi>Printed by Iohn VVolfe</hi> for George Byſhop. 1586.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9998:51"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
